<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of the defeating Card. Mazarine &amp; Oliv. Cromwell's design to have taken Ostend by treachery in the year 1658 written in Spanish by a person of quality (who was a chief actor in the preventing of it) by way of letter to a friend of his presently after the businesse ; since printed in that language, and now translated into English.</title>
            <author>Person of quality.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58440</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">8758683</idno>
  <idno type="VID">41743</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248511599</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R821</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25098</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">08758683</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58440)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41743)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1268:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of the defeating Card. Mazarine &amp; Oliv. Cromwell's design to have taken Ostend by treachery in the year 1658 written in Spanish by a person of quality (who was a chief actor in the preventing of it) by way of letter to a friend of his presently after the businesse ; since printed in that language, and now translated into English.</title>
                  <author>Person of quality.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 132 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Hen. Herringman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1666.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Ostend (Belgium) --  History.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Belgium --  History --  1648-1794.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41743:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41743:1"/>
            <p>A RELATION Of the Defeating
<list>
                  <item>CARD. MAZARINE Design</item>
                  <item>&amp; OLIV. CROMWEL'S Design</item>
               </list> To have Taken <hi>OSTEND</hi> BY Treachery, In the Year, 1658.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN In <hi>Spanish</hi> by a Person of Quality (who was a chief Actor in the preventing of it) by way of Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to a friend of his presently after the businesse.</p>
            <p>SINCE Printed in that Language, and now Translated into English.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fallare falentem non est fraus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Hen. Herringman,</hi> at the <hi>Anchor</hi> in the Lower Walk of the <hi>New Exchange,</hi> 1666.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:41743:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41743:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>ET me perswade thee to bestow two hours upon <hi>Ostend.</hi> What the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> could not compasse (with the vast Expence both of Blood and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure) in a less space than three years, and odd
<pb facs="tcp:41743:3"/> months, thou shalt here find Taken and Retaken in so short a time, that thou mayst truly term it an Adventure of Five Hours. The Intrigue (which is now exposed to the Publick) was spun with so fine a thread, that it was not discernable by the piercing eyes of the quickest-sighted States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in <hi>Christendome:</hi> However he was so far
<pb facs="tcp:41743:3"/> blinded, with zeal, and passion for the service of the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> that he stood in the Dark to many Essentiall Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances, obvious to the meanest capacities. The <hi>English</hi> (although they had but slender parts, to Act in this Tragy-Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy) are notwithstanding brought upon the Stage. <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> the late Tyrant (the Darling
<pb facs="tcp:41743:4"/> Confederate of <hi>France</hi>) upon notice given him of the Design, under the specious pretence of as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting an Allie (but in reallity upon solid motives of pure charity, which always begins at home) was very fairly setting up for himself; but wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly foreseeing the fatall consequence of the losse of so Potent a Friend (whose countenance in
<pb facs="tcp:41743:4"/> that conjuncture of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs was so absolutely necessary to him for the carrying on the Godly work of Reformation of our <hi>English</hi> Nation) he thought good to let his particular Pretensions fall to the ground; and to abandon the whole Booty to the <hi>French;</hi> who (upon confidence of the infallibility of their Minister of State, <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebat
<pb facs="tcp:41743:5"/> enim rumores ante salutem</hi>) were already dividing the spoil of the field; which, what that might amount to upon an improved value, I know not, but as matters were handled, it will appear by the ensuing Narrative, that the chief Adventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers drew Blanks; It being evident to all <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> that his <hi>Eminence</hi> himself (notwithstanding
<pb facs="tcp:41743:5"/> his <hi>parturiunt montes,</hi> &amp;c.) had at last caught a <hi>Tartar. Reader,</hi> to detain thee longer with these Marginal Notes, were to trespass too much upon thy patience, so that I am obliged, by the rules of common Civility, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude my Comment, and to refer thee to the Text it self; having nothing far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to add, but to tell thee, that I do here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
<pb facs="tcp:41743:6"/> thee with a piece of fine <hi>Spanish</hi> Cloath; how it will wear turned, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> know not. Figures revers<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (however they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their proportions) lose much of their native Beauty,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:41743:6"/>
            <head>A LETTER From a person of Worth, to his Friend, upon the <hi>Success</hi> of <hi>OSTEND,</hi> On the 14 of <hi>May,</hi> in the Year <hi>MDCLVIII.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> SHOULD not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve that particular and most inestimable Title of <hi>Friend,</hi> nor comply with the Laws of Friendship, much less with my Obligations, (owing you many) if I did not by this early
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41743:7"/> account make you the first acquainted with the happy success, of one of the strangest and most extravagant Actions that ever was done in War: well may I term it so, since 'tis not to be paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel'd either in Antient or Modern Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story. For although, properly speaking, it were in it self a Stratagem or Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of War, yet was it diversified with such various passages of Tragedy and Farse, so gratefully mix'd and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>santly interwoven, that it might serve for a fit subject to some ingenious Pen, to compose an excellent Comedy. I doubt not but the thunderings of the Cannon, with the confused Relations of many Straglers, did much heighten the curiosity and admiration of all people, and make them swell big with expectation of the event of so sudden and unexpected an Accident. But there is no man can give a more faithful and exact Relation of all that pass'd, nor upon surer grounds than my self; it fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to my share to play one of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41743:7"/> most principal Parts in this Comedy, a Part as dangerous in the Acting, as it was pleasant in the Conclusion. What motive his<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Don John</hi> of <hi>Austria,</hi> then Governour of <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> who is meant by his <hi>Highness</hi> in all this Relation.</note>
               <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> had to engage me (who can no ways pretend to that noble quality of Souldier) in this Military employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I cannot conceive; it seems they were pleased to believe that I was Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster of more cunning than force, and thought I could piece out the Lion's skin with the Fox's tail. God he knows, I was altogether uncapable, of my self; however it was his blessed will to bring me off from this Engagement with Honour and Reputation, as he had done from many others, wherein, to their great satisfaction, I had served both his Majesty and his Highness. Give me leave, Sir, to tell you, 'tis wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy your reflection to consider, what a May-game Fortune makes of the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesses of War, and how from slender
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41743:8"/> and unexpected accidents there do fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently arise such prodigious disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, as do threaten the immediate ruine of a State. You may likewise observe, how the profoundest States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men (notwithstanding their reserved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and precaution, on which they so much rely) do, by ill taking their mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, precipitate themselves into ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reparable errors. But that you may the better come to the conclusion of this business, I shall draw it from the fountain-head.</p>
            <p>I doubt not, Sir, but that you have either known or heard of Colonel <hi>Spintelet,</hi> a Native of this Province, who obtained his Commission by his deserts: He was a person of known va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and one that was no less able to contrive designs, than brisk in the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of them. This Gentleman was forced to flie the <hi>Low-countries</hi> upon the death of an inferiour Officer of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, whom he had killed; and being out of all hopes of obtaining his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,
<pb facs="tcp:41743:8"/> he was resolved to try his fortune in foreign Countries. When he took his leave of his friends (the last com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of a banished man) he told one <hi>Monsieur de Bocq,</hi> a Counsellor at Law, with whom he had a strict amity, That true it was he was going for <hi>France,</hi> but withall he protested upon the word of an honest man, that he would never draw his sword against his King and Liege Lord, notwithstanding he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spaired of ever-returning to his own house. And with these or the like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testations he embarqued for <hi>Zealand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About this same time began Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Mazarini</hi> to hammer upon the anvil of h s brain some new design for the surprising of <hi>Ostend,</hi> having failed in a former attempt in <hi>June</hi> 1648, which had then been set on foot by <hi>Monsieur d' Estrades, Monsieur Servient,</hi> and one <hi>Gentilot</hi> who served under the States General of the Un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces in the Regiment of <hi>Monsieur d' Estrades;</hi> a fair pretext and colour
<pb facs="tcp:41743:9"/> for him to pass to and fro betwixt <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> taking his way by <hi>Ostend</hi> and other Maritine places down to <hi>Calais,</hi> where he had his house and friends. This <hi>Gentilot</hi> being skilful in Fortifications, had observed a notable defect in the Works of <hi>Ostend,</hi> near unto the place where they used to disembarque from the Boats of <hi>Bruges;</hi> and where he thought it most obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to a surprise. There was a little Tavern built of Boards (for the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring of Marriners and other Day-la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers) upon the Cay, at the point of a Bulwark that commanded all within the Haven. This house was so built upon piles, that it took up half the principal Ditch, from whence with a Ladder, or upon Planks, one might (without dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty) pass dry-foot to the aforesaid Bulwark. This house was capable of lodging 200 men with ease, and in my opinion 'twas very feasible to have sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prised us at unawares, by coming on shore as <hi>Hollanders,</hi> and sheltring
<pb facs="tcp:41743:9"/> themselves in the aforesaid house; we having been so remiss and negligent as not to take notice of it before. This Plot was chiefly managed by one <hi>William Ytersun</hi> a Native of <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> who made his escape out of the Town about three or four days before it was surrendred to us in the year, 1652.</p>
            <p>The Cardinal (with those of his Counsel) re-assuming this design, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patcht <hi>Gentilot</hi> to learn, whether there was any alteration made in the Fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations since the year 1648. attributing their former ill success, either to the backwardness, or treachery, of the <hi>Count de Ransaw.</hi> Oh miserable condition of Envy, thus (upon the least miscarriage) to calumniate the most Heroick actions, and to traduce the reputation of so great a Souldier, in recompence of all his services done for the Crown of <hi>France!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being well informed that no altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had been made in the Fortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> (appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending
<pb facs="tcp:41743:10"/> no danger from thence, were wholly attentive to the present motions of the <hi>French</hi> Army) they resolved to find out a fit person to carry on their design, and such an one as had corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spondence and intelligence in the Town, that he might give such notice of the state of affairs, as should be necessary for their purpose.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gentilot</hi> met by chance with one <hi>Livine Ytersun</hi> (Brother to the above-named <hi>William</hi>) who was then in <hi>Paris,</hi> following his own business in quality of a Merchant. This honest man was ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished hence, as being suspected to be privy to his Brother's practices, although in truth he was of other Principles, and did totally abhor them, however he did dissemble it, being in an enemie's country. <hi>Gentilot</hi> was confident this man would be glad of the occasion of doing some remarkable service for <hi>France,</hi> the better to establish and sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the Credit his Brother had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them: wherefore being fully
<pb facs="tcp:41743:10"/> instructed in the business, he was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rought into the presence of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal, and of others his most secret Counsellours; where his Eminence did (with many perswasions, and large pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises, wherein he shewed himself a Doctor of the Chair) so far prevail seemingly upon this <hi>Ytersun,</hi> as to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage him to use his best endeavours in finding out some person that might be fit to transact this business, with that se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecy, and caution as was requisite.</p>
            <p>I have already told you that this <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine</hi> did detest the action his Brother was engaged in, of which he had not the least notice; and he did verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve God Almighty had sent him this intelligence; as a means to do his King some service, by which he might merit his pardon, and return to his Family, the thing in the world he most desired; for by giving information of what he knew, he supposed he should be re-call'd from an exile, which he suffered for the crimes of another man; he likewise
<pb facs="tcp:41743:11"/> thought that by this occasion he migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be serviceable to Colonel <hi>Spintelet,</hi> for whom he had a particular kindness.</p>
            <p>With this intention, and with his former dissimulation, he returned (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accompanied with <hi>Gentilot</hi>) to the Cardinal, promising him to present him with a person very proper for the execution of such a design; a man of courage and experience, one that, to purchase a reputation, and to make a fortune, would check at nothing. He added withal, that his Eminence might confide in him, in regard he was in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spair of ever returning into his own Country, much less into the Kings Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, having committed murder on an Officer of Justice.</p>
            <p>Here began the Comedy, and this was the first Scene; for till now, <hi>Spin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telet</hi> was never spoken of, nor so much as his name known in <hi>France.</hi> There was a large character given of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, extolling to the Skies his wit and courage, and not omitting the cause, I
<pb facs="tcp:41743:11"/> have told you of his banishment. They finding (by what had been said of him) that he was fit for their purpose, forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with commanded <hi>Livine</hi> to seek him out with diligence, and with all possible speed, to bring him to <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Colonel <hi>Spintelet</hi> was at this present in <hi>Zealand,</hi> where <hi>Livine</hi> met with him, and having with great privacy conferred together of all that had passed with the Cardinal and the rest at <hi>Paris,</hi> they agreed at last (like honest men, laying hold on this occasion) to adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise his Highness of what had happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, hoping at the same time, both to gain his favour and discharge their own duties; but being resolved to put a cheat upon the Cardinal, whom they knew eagerly bent upon the surprizing of <hi>Ostend,</hi> they deferred the giving his Highness intelligence, till they had been at <hi>Paris,</hi> and absolutely engaged his Eminence in this Chimera, and seen him lanch't forth into the Main, that they might give a more solid and exact
<pb facs="tcp:41743:12"/> account of all; and try if by making him greedy of that Bait, they might possibly decoy him into the Net, which within a few months after they brought to pass.</p>
            <p>They had not been three hours in <hi>Paris,</hi> when meeting with <hi>Gentilot,</hi> they were brought immediately to his Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, where, close shut up with Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur <hi>D' Estrades</hi> and <hi>Servient,</hi> they held a large conference upon the whole bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness; which debate being continued two or three several days, ended in a resolution of leaving the management, and modelling of the design wholly to <hi>Spintelet,</hi> who (pretending a necessity of speaking with some Confidents of his) alleadged, it would be very conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for him to go back into <hi>Zealand,</hi> &amp; that having disposed businesses there, he would return and give his Eminence a farther accompt. The Cardinal made him an offer of money, Passeport, and Convoy; the money (to confirm his Eminence the more) he refused, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted both Passeport and Convoy.
<pb facs="tcp:41743:12"/> With these kind expressions and offers, the Cardinal thinking he had made all sure; he charged him to pass by <hi>London,</hi> giving him Credential-letters to the Protector, either, because he knew the need he should have of <hi>English</hi> Vessels, or not daring to make so great an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, without giving him notice, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the strict League that was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them.</p>
            <p>These men found not such a Recepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the Protector as they imagined, for he shewed a great distrust of their discourse, either, because he did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire the <hi>French</hi> should make such a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress in <hi>Flanders,</hi> or that he knew more than his Eminence, being more distrust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and having been bred up in a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent School. <hi>Spintelet,</hi> perceiving by his ambiguous and unsignificant Answers, that he did not swallow the Bait kindly, and that he could not gain upon him by his wiles (for his aime was to Trapan them both) he resolved to return to <hi>Zealand,</hi> whence he wrote a Letter to
<pb facs="tcp:41743:13"/> the Councellour <hi>De Bocq,</hi> pressing him to meet him at <hi>Sluce;</hi> for that he had a business to impart to him that did high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly import his Majesties service.</p>
            <p>In this interim there came daily secret advices from <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England</hi> to his Highness, by which he was assured there was a great design hatching against some place upon the Sea Coast; for some gave him notice that Colonel <hi>Spintelet</hi> had been seen to enter into the Cardinals Lodgings at very late hours; others, that he had been in <hi>England,</hi> and there had resorted, as late in the night, to the Protector's. And knowing that the Colonel had frequented no places so much as those near the Sea, they guess'd his design must lye that way. There came several advices of the same nature to his Majesty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> who residing at that time in <hi>Bruges,</hi> communicated them to me, that his Highness might be advertised of them; besides, it was made very evident by the intercepting of several <hi>English</hi> Letters, which came
<pb facs="tcp:41743:13"/> so thick, that the Governours of those places were thereupon particularly warned to stand upon their guard, and had three thousand men sent to re-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force them. This was the cause that the<note n="*" place="margin">The Country Militia.</note>
               <hi>Courlings</hi> remain'd so long in <hi>Ostend,</hi> upon the Countries charge, of which there were lamentable complaints made to his Highness, and the Marquisse of <hi>Cara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cena;</hi> Whence you may learn that those who govern have always particular rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons to themselves for all their actions, which we ought not to pry into nor cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure.</p>
            <p>Councellour <hi>de Bocq</hi> was in <hi>Bergen St. Winoxe</hi> (where he dwelt) when he received this Letter from Colonel <hi>Spin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telet,</hi> which he did immediately com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate to the Marquiss of <hi>Lede,</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral by Sea and Governour of <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk,</hi> the only person of Authority that was at hand; desiring to know, whether he did approve of his giving him a meeting; and informing the Marquiss
<pb facs="tcp:41743:14"/> withall of the discourse they two had had upon the Colonels going for <hi>France.</hi> The Marquisse presently commanded him, that without delay, he should go away to <hi>Sluce,</hi> to hear what he had to propose; for there could be no harm in hearing any propositions, since a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst many that are alleadged by such people, there often falls out somewhat of advantage, and 'tis always in the power of him that Governs to do what he thinks best.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>De Bocq</hi> being come to <hi>Sluce,</hi> had a large relation made him by his friend, of all that had pass'd with the Cardinal and the rest at <hi>Paris</hi> touching the design on foot, all which the Counsellour set down in writing; and the Colonel added to all the particulars, that, if his Highness would give him leave, and be pleas'd to assist (the Cardinal being already so eager upon it, by the hopes he had put him in) he would insensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly plunge him into so great a mischief, and the King should receive so conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb facs="tcp:41743:14"/> a service, as he hoped would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline his Majesty to grant him the grace he so passionately desired, which was to return to his own Country; for although 'tis an ordinary saying, <hi>Omne solum forti patria,</hi> yet is there no home so sweet as a man's own.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>De Bocq</hi> did very much commend them for proceeding with so much zeal and fidelity, assuring them, it was the only way they could pitch upon, both to return home with honour and reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and also to deserve a recompence (a great satisfaction to people in dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace to be able to work themselves out of the briers by serving their Prince) and thereby to obtain not only favour and honour, but withall to gain prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. They took leave the one of the other, with a resolution to meet again, exchanging Notes and Ciphers for the carrying on a correspondency.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>De Bocq</hi> went away immediately to <hi>Brussels,</hi> where he gave an accompt at large of all that had passed to his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
<pb facs="tcp:41743:15"/> who recommended to him in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> first place secresie, in the second he gave him charge to feed his friends still with hopes, whilst he considered what wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be done for the future; for Princes (as wise men hold) ought not to be carried away with the first reports, but to weigh them throughly, if their time will permit: But above all his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness commanded him to hasten to <hi>Ostend,</hi> and to inform the Governour of what had passed, that he might be ready to prevent any inconveniency that might interfere, with the intelligence given him by <hi>de Bocq,</hi> a timely and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary precaution. There was then Governour of the Town <hi>Don Barnabe de Vargas Machuca,</hi> Knight of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Saint <hi>Jago</hi> a Master of the Camp, and Serjeant Major General, who raised himself by his valour (having run through all the Offices of the <hi>Spanish</hi> Infantry) to this eminent charge; a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son fit for higher imployments.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41743:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>De Bocq</hi> was not long in going to <hi>Ostend,</hi> where he much surprised the Governour with this Relation; who making reflections upon the Fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the place, especially of that little Tavern formerly spoken of, found the business to be really of Concern, and that our Enemies had not ill ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served that notorious defect. So he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately caus'd the little house to be thrown down, which being done in half an hour, he planted new Palisa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does on the Counter-scarp, with Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riers; he likewise built a Redoubt of Stone at the point of the Cay, capable of holding fifty Musqueteers with se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity. In fine, he did (according to his accustomed care and diligence) all that military experience could suggest to him, for the safety of the place; so that having a recruit of men sent him, he made all sure on that part.</p>
            <p>The news of the alteration of the Fortifications was quickly buzz'd into the ears of the <hi>Mazarinites,</hi> who were
<pb facs="tcp:41743:16"/> all this while hatching of rotten eggs, treating with the Colonel of Chime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra's, and building Castles in the Air; yet notwithstanding they thought the business cock-sure. At this they were much startled, and upon the point o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> desisting, when <hi>Spintelet</hi> (who had hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> arguments ready at his fingers ends) dissembling the business with a cheerful countenance, began to lay a new Trap for them; he wished them to be of good courage, and bad them not to doubt of seeing <hi>Ostend</hi> very suddenly in the hands of his most Christian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty; for that it was an usual thing with all Governours, upon their first coming to their Government, to be tampering, and to alter something in the Fortifications, every one according to his own Capricho, and skill. That although the taking of the Town by the way that had then been laid, was very practicable; yet since there was no remedy, there was a necessity of finding out some other expedient,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41743:16"/> which he had at hand, very easie and safe, without either charge or hazard of men; and he assured them, that as soon as he had received some Letters, which he pretended to expect from <hi>Brussels,</hi> he would then acquaint them both with the manner and method; and perceiving they began to give an ear to his discourse, he requested of them onely three or four days time, intending in the interim to learn his Highness pleasure what was to be done for the future.</p>
            <p>The Frenchmen all this while never suspected Counsellor <hi>de Bocq,</hi> who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways kept them company, and passed as a Kins-man of the Colonels, by the name of <hi>Monsieur Stappin,</hi> and so make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing them believe that he sent him to <hi>Ostend</hi> to negotiate the business, <hi>de Bocq</hi> went directly to <hi>Brussels</hi> to receive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions from his Highness. He made a quick return from thence, with pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Orders from his Highness, that they should lay their heads together to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41743:17"/> agree betwixt themselves how (by amusing and cajolling them) to draw them into a snare. And the Colone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> having assured them that this was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> person they might as safely rely upon, as upon himself, they did not in the least distrust him.</p>
            <p>The Colonel did declare to them, that he had two Kinsmen of his and his Wife's in <hi>Ostend,</hi> Captains of the <hi>Walloon</hi> Foot, and that there was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, who was within two or three days to enter into the Town with his Company, who although he were not allied to him, yet he was an intimate friend, in whom he did entirely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side; that these parties were very wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the <hi>Spanish</hi> service, in regard their Arrears were kept back, and that many other affronts were put upon them by the Governour, and that they desired nothing more (if occasion served) than to quit their employment, and to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Fortune where ever she led them; that for many months he had fed them
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41743:17"/> with hopes, &amp; he believ'd them very ripe for mutiny, as well to relieve their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessities (having spent themselves to their shirts in maintaining their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies) as to revenge the injuries they had receiv'd. That they had above 400 men in their three Companies, all old Souldiers, being the remainder of his Regiment, who much coveted to return under his command. That in <hi>Ostend</hi> there were but few <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and those very feeble and heartless, yet they did so tyrannize over the poor neighbouring people, that many of them daily quitted their habitations; and if those that did remain could but meet with any reasonable conditions, one might infallibly dispose of the one and the other, and that if any party did but appear in the Haven, and present themselves before the Town, they would receive them in, and shake off the <hi>Spanish</hi> yoke. To this intent they were to make Capitulations with the Neighbours and Towns-men; and as
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41743:18"/> to the Soldiers, that should be his care But that they might not think slightly of the design, he prepared them with a discourse of three or four conditions, which without doubt were such a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would soonest inveigle them. The firs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thing they were to promise to the Neighbours, was, that there should be no other than the Roman Catholic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Religion exercised in that place. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, That they would maintain the antient Privileges and Customs of the Town, that they would pay the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers all the Arrears due to them from the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> as soon as they should be Masters of rhe Place, but not before. As for their own recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence and those that belonged to them, they would wholly rely upon his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Majesty, and his Eminence, with whom they would not capitulate as to their particular interest, alledging that so brave a King and so great a Minister could not but reward them a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cording to the merits of their service.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:41743:18"/>
            <p>These discourses did relish so well with those who managed the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal's business, that they presently rode away to <hi>Paris</hi> to give an accompt of them; and returned very suddenly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oaden with instructions and promises, much larger than the first. Neither did ours sleep the while, but were as busie with his <hi>Highness;</hi> of whom they begg'd leave, that they might make use of two Captains names, <hi>Horns</hi> and <hi>Sney<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs,</hi> notwithstanding they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves were wholly ignorant of the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness: That, in case the <hi>French-men</hi> should make enquiry by any other means, whether there were such Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains in <hi>Ostend,</hi> they might find all things to agree in what <hi>Spintelet</hi> told them.</p>
            <p>Having procured this permission from his Highness, <hi>de Bocq</hi> departed with Monsieur <hi>de Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter</hi> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rother-in-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aw to <hi>Spintelet,</hi> one that had no slender part to act in this Farce) and with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his acquaintance, who repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41743:19"/> the two aforesaid Captains. There needed not much Rhetorick to perswade these <hi>French-men,</hi> that there was no manner of doubt of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cting whatever the Colonel had proposed to them; with which they were so trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, that they dispatched away a Messenger of their own, with the news to the Cardinal, who was so tickled with the hopes of success, that his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer (mixt with new promises) seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be brought back with the Wind, it came so speedily.</p>
            <p>They did with an unanimous consent agree, that from thence forward only <hi>de Bocq</hi> (or, to speak more properly, <hi>Stappin,</hi> for that was the name they knew him by) should write all the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of those Captains and Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates to the Colonel, and from the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel to them; and that he should be the sole director of the Conspiracy, as being the best Scholar, the read<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>est at his pen, and one that was the least to be suspected in regard his busin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lay in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41743:19"/> several places. Having thus disp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sed their affairs, and having procured a Passeport for Monsieur <hi>de winter</hi> and Captain <hi>Sprui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (who went by the names of <hi>Horns</hi> and <hi>Sneyers</hi>) they parted for that time, each man pretending to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his own occasions.</p>
            <p>About this time, Mareshall <hi>Turene</hi> having newly taken Saint <hi>Venant,</hi> and <hi>Montmedy,</hi> came with his Victorious Army to <hi>Watten,</hi> from whence he wrote letters to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ardinal, to sign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fie to him that great Crisis; and to let him know, that he was then upon the point of making himself Master of all <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> in case the Confederates, whom they had mentioned to him, were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to perform their part. The Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal hereupon gave speedy notice of this to his Creatures, that they might be in a readiness, with the Colonel and the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st of the Cabal, to put their d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sign in execution. Upon this, <hi>Spi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>telet</hi> desired some time to acquaint his Camarades with it, and in the inter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m dispatches a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41743:20"/> Messenger of his own to Counsellour <hi>de Bocq,</hi> to inform his <hi>Highness</hi> how things were, and to know what answer he would please they should make. His <hi>Highness</hi>'s Will being known, <hi>de Bocq</hi> wrote (as from the Confederates) that it was impossible to do the work at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, in regard there were 2, or 3000. Boors that were fled for shelter into <hi>Ostend,</hi> for fear of the <hi>French</hi> Army; so they humbly besought his <hi>Eminence,</hi> that he would in no sort permit the Army to advance upon any expedition into that Province; for so long as the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>santry were refug'd in those Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, they kept double Guards, and we being not Masters of the Field, should be forced to draw our men into them, which would absolutely ruin the design that was so well contriv'd. Upon this, Mareshall <hi>Turene</hi> had orders, not to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt <hi>Linque, Mardique,</hi> nor <hi>Berghen,</hi> those places being thought of small im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, that the Army might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume it self upon them, and this fair op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41743:20"/> be slipt; and that if once <hi>Ostend</hi> were taken, those other places with <hi>Dunkirk</hi> and <hi>Newport</hi> would fall in of themselves, since 'twas certain the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> would be forced to abandon them. It was likewise urged, that the Army might have strict Orders to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean themselves fairly, and to use the Country people civilly, so that they might be encouraged to return home to their own houses, by which means <hi>Ostend</hi> would be cleared of them, and all lets removed that could retard their design. There was a Gentleman dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patcht away to the <hi>Cardinal,</hi> with a particular relation of what posture their business was in. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>se reasons before mentioned, with what the Messenger added of his own head, concerning the great confidence he left them in of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passing their ends; did so far prevail with his <hi>Eminence,</hi> that he sent away two Posts, one at the heels of the other, with express orders to Mareshal <hi>Turene</hi> not to dislodge the Army from their
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41743:21"/> present station, nor to engage upon any design, till they saw what this Treaty would come to. 'Twas as clear as day, that the Cardinal had swallowed the Bait, and that his orders were pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually observed by the Mareshall; for in six week, after, he permitted not a man to stir out of his Quarters, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the great hardship they suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but kept them in as close as if they apprehended the beating up of their Quarters. At this all <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> stood amazed, except only such who were privy to the Intrigue.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the Cardinal did by letters urge those that were in <hi>Zealand</hi> to expedite the business; they likew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>se earnestly pressed <hi>Spintelet,</hi> who was now put to his trumps, being destitute of further excuses for delay: At last having failed of an answer to two or three letters, which he wrote to <hi>de Bocq</hi> concerning the business, and finding the date of the Passeport, he had from his <hi>Highness,</hi> ready to expire; he resolved
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41743:21"/> to go towards <hi>Bruges</hi> to inform himself where <hi>de Bocq</hi> was, and to find out a conveniency of sending letters to him, and to learn from him his <hi>Highness</hi> pleasure for the future. Whereupon, under pretence of going to conferre with his Associates (and to give them notice of the haste his <hi>Eminence</hi> desired them to make) he took leave of the <hi>French-men</hi> for four or five days, with a firm resolution of returning within that time; and so he came to the Suburbs of <hi>Bruges,</hi> which they call <hi>Schipstael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It so happened (to his misfortune) that there was no Field-officer of the Army then there; wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fore <hi>Spintelet,</hi> knowing me to be well acquainted with Councellour <hi>de Bocq,</hi> thoug t I could inform him where he was, as likewise that by my interest at Court, I could either get his Passeport renewed, or at leastwise know what it was his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness would have to be done. To this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd he (knowing that I dw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lt there) sent a Towns-man to me, a friend of his,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41743:22"/> to desire me to come privately to him to conferre about some matters of great importance.</p>
            <p>I (who looked upon him as a noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Rebell, engaged in the highest Treason imaginable, and found that he was of a turbulent spirit, by the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which were intercepted by the King of <hi>England</hi>'s Ministers, who did then reside there; as likewise by the Spies which I maintained in <hi>Sluce</hi> to pry into his designs, of which I had already ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertized his <hi>Highness,</hi> and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiss of <hi>Caracena;</hi> who without d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abusing me, or acquainting me with any thing of what had passed between them, did highly commend my care and zeal, commanding me to continue all possible vigilancy, and to give them no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of what I could discover of his Plots, and to inform the Governours of the Maritine Towns) I could not, I say, think it safe for me to communicate alone with so suspected a person, whom I knew to be imploy'd about some dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41743:22"/> design; wherefore, to comply with my duty, I desired both the assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of the Magistrates of <hi>Bruges,</hi> under whose jurisdiction I was; and likewise leave from the chief of the <hi>Franc</hi> to apprehend him, supposing I should do his Majesty an especial piece of Service, in securing such a person, and giving his <hi>Highness</hi> notice of it.</p>
            <p>It was thought fit that the Scout of the Town, together with the chief Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gomaster, the Serjeant Major of the Count <hi>de Megem,</hi> and some other Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, should bring him in a Coach to the house of the <hi>Franc,</hi> which was done in less than half an hours space. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider, Sir upon how weak a Basis human designs are built: for whil'st <hi>Spintelet</hi> on his part, and I on m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne (both with an equal zeal) thought to do for the best, we were in a moment like to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed so great a Business.</p>
            <p>The Colonel, foreseeing that if his being clapt up were divulged (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise he valued not his being in hold)
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41743:23"/> it would be the cause of the miscarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of the Plot, which he conceived so well laid; he resolved to disclose to me the bottom of the Secret, supposing that I, receiving it from his own mouth, would give credit to it, and thereupon dismisse him; whereby his imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not being further noised, would not come to the knowledge of those in <hi>Zealand.</hi> But thanks be to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od I was not ignorant, that it was neither conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, nor safe, to hear singly the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of any suspected person, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I refused it, unless there were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent some sufficient witness, that could at any time attest our d scourse; and both of us agreeing upon Monsieur <hi>de Blend,</hi> the<note n="*" place="margin">Or Register.</note> Greffier, and chief Pensioner of the Town, who was near at hand; we passed our words each to other to observe secresie, upon which he laid open to me the whole Stratagem at large.</p>
            <p>The news of the imprisonment of the Traytor <hi>Spintelet,</hi> being in an instant
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41743:23"/> spread all over the Country, did very much trouble those in <hi>Zealand,</hi> who waited his return with great impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. They fail'd not to advertise the Count <hi>de Charau,</hi> Governour of <hi>Calais,</hi> who immediately dispatched one to Mareshall <hi>Turene</hi> with the ill news.</p>
            <p>But to return to our Prisoner: Upon our questioning him what papers he had about him, we found one Passe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port from the <hi>French</hi> King, with the names of the aforesaid Captains, and another from <hi>Don John,</hi> which height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned our distrust, to see the Dispatches of two opposite Princes directed to one person; so 'twas agreed, that I should write to the Marquiss of <hi>Cara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cena</hi> (in my accustomed Cypher to his Excellence) all that had been rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to us by the Colonel; and that the Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffier should set down, in a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar paper, what had been said by me; and that in the interim while we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected an answer, we should lodge the Colonel in the Town-prison, for fear
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:41743:24"/> of the worst, not daring upon our own score, to trust him in any private house.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Highness,</hi> and his <hi>Excellence,</hi> who were then at <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> were high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dissatisfied with this news which was brought them by a Passe from the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son. But seeing that on our part we acted with integrity, and that what was done, could not be undone (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they now repented their not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting me with their transactions, considering the daily advices I gave them of the private meetings that their Enemies had with the Colonel in <hi>Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and knowing that I had pitch't my Net<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to catch him, being encouraged to it by them;) at last they resolved, with all diligence, to send Counsellour <hi>de Bocq</hi> to me, with an Order to deliver him up the Prisoner, with some pretext of his having broke prison.</p>
            <p>There happened an accident to <hi>de Bocq</hi> in this journey, which was like to put a period both to the business and to his life: For coming into <hi>Newport</hi> (and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:41743:24"/> passing at a late hour through the Town to save his Tide, that he might get with speed to <hi>Ostend</hi>) he unhappi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y met with the round of the Guards of some of the Country-people, who upon these Alarums were lodged all along the Sea coast, with order to take or kill who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever should he found to be walking late upon the Downs, or on the Sands, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Watch-word; so that he escaped narrowly of being kno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kt on the head by these Boors. But he giving them to understand, that he knew several of the Officers under whose Command they were (having p llaged and dry-basted him) they drag'd him about half a league to Monsieur <hi>de Blome</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Sheriffe.</note>
               <hi>Eschevind</hi> of the <hi>Franc,</hi> who knowing him rescued him out of their unm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rcifull hands, and so half dead with their ill usage, he made a shift to reach <hi>Ostend;</hi> where causing himself to be let blood, after a short conference with the Governour, he got out of Town about four of the clock, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41743:25"/> came to my house early; where, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my Orders, we consulted of some means to free <hi>Spintelet</hi> from pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, without giving any ground of jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousie that we understood one another.</p>
            <p>There was a Wagon provided to wait them at the shutting of the gates, that they might go together to <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> but it was a hard task to find any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text that would take with the City, to make them credit the escape of so no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious a person; wherefore to disguise the business the more, it was noised abroad, that there had been a drinking-frollick amongst the prisoners, and that in a drunken humour they had forced the Keeper and his Domesticks; and that the Colonel, with several prisoners for debt, had made their escape. The Goaler going three or four days about the Town with his head bound up, as if he had really been wounded, and soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing of friends to mediate with the Magistrates for him, that he might not for this neglect lose his place (which
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:41743:25"/> the more to amuse the world was threatned) it seemed all was done that possibly could in such a case.</p>
            <p>Here it was that I first began to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riddle the mystery, and to dive unto the bottome of the design, which none of this Town, nor of those Magistrates knew, till many months after they found by the succ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ss, with what dexterity and cunning the business had been carried on.</p>
            <p>As soon as ever the news came to Mareshall <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urene,</hi> that <hi>Spintelet</hi> was taken prisoner, he gave the design of surprizing <hi>Oslend</hi> for lost; and without waiting for further orders from Court, he advanced with his Army to <hi>Mardike,</hi> of which he became Master in a few days. At the same time Colonel <hi>Spin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telet</hi> returned to <hi>Zealand,</hi> disguised with a false beard, and a strange habit; and, with many smooth and quaint discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, related to them the particulars of his miraculous Escape, convincing them with evident circumstances, shewing them letters of greater assurances than
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41743:26"/> ever they had of compassing their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign, and arguing that it was apparent that God Almighty permitted it should come to passe, and co-operated with them, since he had so wonderfully deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered him out of the clutches of his enemies: Moreover, that during the time that he lay secretly in <hi>Bruges</hi> (where likewise were many male-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents) he had been visited by some of his Confederates, who had given him such hopes of good success, that it was infallible, in case Mareshall <hi>Turene</hi> would withdraw his Army, and not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance upon any other design, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in those parts; for that would give such jealousie to his <hi>Highness</hi> and the Generals, that to secure those places they would certainly draw the body of the Army into them, not being strong enough to keep the Field▪ and then it would be impossible to effect their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign. To confirm them the more, he shewed them letters from Councellour <hi>de Bocq,</hi> who (as I told you before)
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41743:26"/> went under the name of <hi>Stappin,</hi> and chief of the Conspiratours, alleadging the same reasons on their part, which he constantly received from his <hi>Highness</hi> to spin out time, and to delude the <hi>French</hi> with expectation.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Highness</hi> commanded me at the same time (going to <hi>Dunkirk</hi> about some business) that upon my return to <hi>Bruges,</hi> I should, if it were possible, see the Colonel, without giving any suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, or being seen at <hi>Sluce,</hi> whither I was to go. Being come thither, by a private m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ssage I sent to him, I easily contrived our meeting out of the Town, to know of him how the <hi>French</hi> stood affected, and what they thought of his escape, and whether they persisted in what they had begun. His <hi>Highness</hi>'s chiefest care being how to make his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage by prolonging the execution of the Plot they were so fond of.</p>
            <p>The Colonel kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w so well to cajole them, and his arguments were so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, that they were more confident
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41743:27"/> than ever of their designs, and so pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent were the letters which were shewn them from <hi>de Bocq,</hi> that they sent away a Messenger of their own with them to the Cardinal, in whom they made no lesse impression; for he immediately dispatch'd away an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press to the Mareshall, that whether <hi>Mardike</hi> were taken or not taken, he should suddenly without losing time retire on this side the River <hi>A.</hi> The Mareshall punctually obeyed his orders, without stopping at any inconveniency, though the ways in those parts were so spoiled by the continual rains, and the waters so deep, that the passages were inaccessible. Some of his Cannon, with above a thousand Carts and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, were left in the mire; besides there mouldred away more than three thousand of his men in this retreat, which made all <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Flanders</hi> astonished at this sudden Action.</p>
            <p>The Cardinal was not backward in making his complaints to his correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41743:27"/> in <hi>Zealand,</hi> that at the request of the Colonel and his associates, he had withdrawn the Army, and done on his part all that was required of him, pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing them to avoid all delayes on their side, adding fresh offers of money, with promises of great rewards. These letters pass'd from <hi>Spintelet's</hi> hands to <hi>de Bocq,</hi> and from his were with speed conveyed to his <hi>Highness</hi> for fresh instructions.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t being very necessary to find out some new pretence for delays, to carry the cheat on the better; his <hi>Highness</hi> thought fit that <hi>de Bocq</hi> should, in the name of the Confiderates, write to the Colonel that all things were now ready for action, and that they were highly satisfied to find their design so infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and it being likewise requisite that they on their part should forecast and provide all things possible, there rested but one scruple or let which they sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected might impede their proceedings, for they said they studied night and day to remove all obstructions. But this
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41743:28"/> was of great importance, That the <hi>English▪</hi> Ships which did ride before <hi>Ostend,</hi> might at the very instant that the business was to be put in execution, hinder the <hi>French</hi> Boats from coming in, detaining them perchance three or four tides, till they had acquainted the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector with it; especially, being netled that they had no share in the enterprise, which would undoubtedly disappoint their so much wish'd for expedition, with the hazard of the lives and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes of all such as should be found in the Town to have had a hand in it; therefore 'twas expedient to require Passeports of the <hi>Protectour,</hi> and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for his Ships to give all requisite assistance, which in regard of the strict League and Amity betwixt them, would not be hard to obtain.</p>
            <p>This obstacle was signified by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press Messenger called <hi>Payen,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Preacher of <hi>Dover,</hi> who had been en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in the business: The Cardinal found this so necessary to be redress'd,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:41743:28"/> that he sent away this <hi>Payen</hi> to <hi>London</hi> to Monsieur <hi>de Bourdeaux,</hi> who was the <hi>French</hi> King's Ambassadour there; charging him to give the <hi>Protectour</hi> speedy notice of the design, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure such dispatches from him, as <hi>Payen</hi> should tell him were necessary.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> not confiding in <hi>Payen's</hi> relation, thinking the business to be absolutely dash'd by the imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Spintelet</hi> (the news of which was quickly spread abroad) and desiring to inform himself more particularly, he sent for <hi>Payen</hi> late one night to examine the matter; who recounting to him by degrees all that the Colonel had made him believe, he did so smoothly and cunningly set forth the whole business, and made it appear so practicable, that <hi>Cromwell</hi> was tickled with the thoughts of it, and began to deal with <hi>Payen</hi> to change the Scene, and to act for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest of the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> at last he wonn <hi>Payen</hi> wholly to himself, having out-brib'd the Cardinal by a Bar
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41743:29"/> and a half, and so it 'twas agreed upon betwixt themselves, that <hi>Payen</hi> should go over into <hi>Zealand</hi> to negotiate w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th <hi>Spintelet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Minister (by vertue of an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from the <hi>Protectour</hi>) found a vessel of 30. pieces of ordnance ready in the <hi>Downs</hi> to transport him into <hi>Zealand,</hi> with instructions, credentials, and all possible allurements, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch he thought might wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k with <hi>Spintelet</hi> and his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marades; offering much more ample, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vantageous conditions than the Cardinal. The Minister, coming into <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d,</hi> by making some excuse, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled to his Companions his going over to <hi>Sluce</hi> to treat on the behalf of the <hi>Protectour,</hi> contrary to the trust and confidence reposed in him by the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. So slight is the faith of many of that Nation, &amp; so prevalent a devil is money.</p>
            <p>The Minister was not backward in soliciting the Colonel, shewing him his large Commission and Instructions, which reached to mountains of gold. The
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41743:29"/> Colonel overjoyed at this occasion of new delays, answered, very cunningly, that he could not treat alone without <hi>Stappin</hi> and the other Confederates; wherefore he required some time, which was the most his <hi>Highness</hi> expected from that business.</p>
            <p>The said <hi>de Bocq</hi> going with speed to <hi>Brussels,</hi> to give his <hi>Highness</hi> this fresh intelligence, was commanded w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th all possible artifice to embrace the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi>'s motion, making shew as if he did entirely dedicate the design to him, enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining him with treating of conditions; so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e returned with all dil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gence to <hi>Sluce,</hi> pret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nding to come from <hi>stend,</hi> with the resolution of the other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates; and entring into conference with <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yen,</hi> after many d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mands and answers (that he might not s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>em to sell his wares at too too low a rate) they came at last to agree, That the Town of <hi>Ostend,</hi> and whatever depended on it, should be put into the <hi>Protectour</hi>'s possession, he not disturbing, or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieting
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:41743:30"/> them in their Religion; and that for the exercise of Calvinism they might take any house in the Town, but not meddle with any of the Churches, and that they should pay down upon the nail one hundred thousand pound Sterling; but as for the gratifying <hi>Stappin,</hi> and the other Officers, that should be left wholly to the <hi>Protectour</hi>'s discretion. There was one Monsieur <hi>de Winter</hi> (Brother-in-law to <hi>Spintelet</hi>) who did not a little contribute to the striking up of this Bargain, passing under the name of Captain <hi>Horns,</hi> whose part he had acted, before he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the Go-between, and Broker in this affair.</p>
            <p>The Minister returns with these Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles into <hi>England,</hi> whence he present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wrote to <hi>Spintelet,</hi> how well he was received by the <hi>Protectour,</hi> who had ratified all the Capitulations, and was now dispatching him to finish the work, and that he would be with him within very few days.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:41743:30"/>
            <p>The French Embassadour being sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til, found (by the <hi>Protectour</hi>'s delaying those dispatches for which he solicited) that he treated the business for himself; whereupon he sent away an Express to the <hi>Cardinal</hi> with his sense, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to presse the granting his demands: and to adde threats to them, intimating that he knew the <hi>Protectour</hi>'s meaning and intentions, and alleaging that it did not consist with the laws of Alliance, to take a business out of his hands, which for six months together he had transacted, and look't upon it as already hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> own. <hi>Payen,</hi> perceiving the <hi>Protectour</hi> wax cold in the business, judging that either he feared the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal,</hi> or that he was not sound at heart, and fearing lest they might fail with both, he wrote to the Colonel, that there was no good to be done with the <hi>English;</hi> ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fore he should be careful how he gave a jealousie to the <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> or abandon those that treated on the behalf of the <hi>Cardinal.</hi> And hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:41743:31"/> at the instance of the Embassadour procured dispatches to those <hi>English</hi> who were in the Rode, that they should not obstruct their passage, he returned to <hi>Spintelet;</hi> urging him that, now there was no farther scruple to be made, he would perform what he had so long and often promised; to which he could make no reply, but that he would not fail to do his part.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Highness</hi> perceiving there was no hopes of drawing the <hi>English</hi> into the trap, and that they had already spent the Autumn and the Winter in these practices, and now the Spring was at hand, and that they could no longer spin out delays, nor find out new pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texts to deferr the execution of what the others did so eagerly gape after; he thought to gain some days by treating of Conditions to be Signed on both sides, for as yet there was nothing of that nature in writing; so they agreed upon the ensuing Articles, which were intituled as followeth:</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="articles">
                        <pb n="51" facs="tcp:41743:31"/>
                        <head>Articles by which Colonel <hi>Spin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telet</hi> and his Confederates do agree, to deliver up the Town and Port of <hi>Ostend,</hi> into the hands of his most Christian Majesty, and his Eminence Cardinal <hi>Mazarini;</hi> upon which his Majesty, and his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence do promise to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form these Conditions follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>FIRST his Majesty on his part shall be obliged to send eight <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>undred choise men wi h their Officers, which shall lie in the Rode, to be ready to enter the Town, upon such sign given by the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel, as shall be agreed upon. That the said Officers and Souldiers (receiving the Pilots, which shall be sent to them in small Boats, which for that purpose are to be had
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:41743:32"/> in a readiness) shall, upon the sign given, enter into the said Haven, at such place as the Colonel shall appoint.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>That the Sieur</hi> de Roumignac <hi>(who was said to be Marshall</hi> de Camp) <hi>should enter at the same time with those men, and that he should bring along with him two hundred thousand Florins, to distribute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the Souldiery.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>This was the cond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tion promised to the Souldiers and under-Officers: But you must also know (that you may the better judge how the game went) that this <hi>Roumignac</hi> was a Snap, which in <hi>France</hi> they call a <hi>Filou,</hi> a married man; yet notwithstanding he had promised to marry the Daughter of the Colonel, who was to be left Governour of the Town: This they privately agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betwixt themselves, alt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ough the Colonel knew all his tricks w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ll e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and that they play'd<note n="*" place="margin">Turk against Moor.</note>
                           <hi>Corsario à Corsavio.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <pb n="53" facs="tcp:41743:32"/>
                        <p>
                           <hi>That these</hi> 800. <hi>men, in pursuance of the orders given them by</hi> Roumignac <hi>and</hi> Spintelet, <hi>should possess themselves of the Walls and Magazins; and that there should be a Proclamation set forth, that no man, under pain of death, should en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>er the house of any Burgher upon what pretence soever.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>That the said Colonel shou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>d remain Governour of the place, and that all the Souldiery, Magazins, Ammunition, and whatever belonged to the Town should con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue under his Command, till such time as his Majesty should have consigned into the hands of the Colonel, the summe of</hi> 400000. <hi>Crowns to be distributed amongst his (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marades; which said s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>mme being satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, he was to re-deliver the place, with all that belonged to it, in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>o the hands of the Sieur</hi> de Roumignac, <hi>who was to keep it till farther order from his m st Christian Maj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>sty.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>That all the Towns-men, and Citizens should continue the Apostolical Roman faith, not permitting in the Town any Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41743:33"/> or Conventicle of what Sect soever; And also that the Towns-men and Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, should be maintained and conserved in all their Rights, Customes, Priviledges, and Immunities, which they enjoy under the Government of the most Catholick King; and that they should continue the posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of their goods, moveables and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveables, of what quality soever, both within and without the limits of the City.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And that all those who had been Actors in this business, and should be nominated by the said</hi> Spintelet, <hi>might passe with their families and goods to any Town of</hi> France, <hi>or to any place under the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the most Chr stian King; where they were to enjoy all freedome and privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge without being subject to free-quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, lodging of Souldiers, taxes, or impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions, which were paid by other Vassals of</hi> France; <hi>and their Widdows and Children, both Sons and Daughters, should enjoy the same priviledge.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>That if it should happen, that because of this service done by t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>em, the enemies
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41743:33"/> of</hi> France <hi>should ruin them, or fire their houses or goods of what quality soever they were, or should by way of revenge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiscate their rents; if they could make suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient proofs of it, his Majesty should be obliged to rebuild them, and to make their losses good to them, and at his own proper cost and charges, to re-instate them in their former condition; unless his Majesty should think convenient to recompence them with equal value, and satisfie them with other goods. And that all such who should de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to reside in</hi> France, <hi>should have the priviledge of being naturalized, and made capable of bearing any Office in</hi> France, <hi>and be exempted from the forfeit of their goods to the King at their death: In fine, to be treated in all respects, without any manner of distinction, as naturall</hi> French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>That his Majesty, as soon as they shall be Masters of the Town, do cause these Articles to be published, (in his Royall name) in the Town-house the by sound of a Bell, and to have Copies of them set upon
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:41743:34"/> the Gates, and other publck places of the City.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Lastly, that his Majesty should com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand two hundred thousand</hi> Florins <hi>more to be put into the hands of</hi> John Gerrard (<hi>one of the</hi> Cardinal<hi>'s Agents) to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed for Ammunition, Fortifications, Victuals, and other necessaries; lest the</hi> Spaniards <hi>should return and assault the Town in those places where the Fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were defective, and that the said</hi> Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard <hi>should be obliged to give an accompt to such person or persons as his Majesty should appoint; and upon his Majesties accepting of these conditions, they were ready <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>o perform what they had promised.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>With these Capitulat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ons, which <hi>Don John</hi> had composed for his pleasure, Councellour <hi>de Bocq</hi> came down to <hi>Sluce;</hi> and with great d ssimulation, as if he had come from <hi>Ostend,</hi> he deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Letter, in the names of the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates, to those Setters imployed by the <hi>Cardinal,</hi> which contained in sum,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:41743:34"/> That whereas they were now ready, and upon the point of putting into the hands of his most Christian Majesty, so important a place as <hi>Ostend,</hi> the only Harbour that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> had in these Countries (by which means, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either losse or charge, he made him Master of the whole Country) it was but fit that on their parts they should have some assurance of the reward and satisfaction, which they expected from the King for the common Souldiers, to whom these Confederates had pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised all their Arrears, with some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing over and above; and they found themselves obliged to require some real assurance thereof from the King, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall to satisfie them; neither could they refuse to grant them so just a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest, and therefore presented those Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles in their behalf; but for what concerned the Colonel, and the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains <hi>Horns, Sneyers,</hi> and <hi>Spruyt,</hi> they cast themselves wholly upon his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties goodness and favour.</p>
                        <pb n="58" facs="tcp:41743:35"/>
                        <p>It was necessary to send away these Capitulations presently, by one of those Agents, to the <hi>Cardinal,</hi> who till then thought he had to deal with fools; but finding them (at the end of 8. months time when he thought all was safe) to come out with these cross-grain'd Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions, he had much ado to dissemble his resentment; however he cast out some expressions, as if it were not well done, after so long a time, to start other Proposals than what were proposed at first, and seemed much troubled, ere he could resolve what to do. But the Messenger played his part so well, set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth the sincerity, and plain deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Flemmings;</hi> that, after a few days, there came forth an Order from the King to Marshall <hi>D' Aumont,</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorizing him, and giving him absolute power, to conclude this treaty; A Copy whereof translated, is as followeth.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:41743:35"/>
                  <head>To our dear and well-beloved Sieur <hi>D' Aumont</hi> Marshall of <hi>France,</hi> of our Councell of State, Knight of our Orders, Colonel of the Guards of our Person, and Governour of our City and Castle of <hi>Boloigne</hi> with the Precincts thereof.</head>
                  <p>WHEREAS many wel-affected to our Crown have made several advantagious Overtures of designs and enterprizes for the good of our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and whereas for the effecting of them, it is necessary to treat with them about the reward and recompence they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend; and finding no person fitter than your self to manage such a busin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ss, by reason of your prudence and great experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; having had transactions of all sorts of affairs pass'd through your hands, of which y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u have always given a good accompt:
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:41743:36"/> We therefore think fit to Elect, Constitute, and Depute you, as by these presents, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified under our hand, We do Constitute and Depute you, that in Our name you do attend, consider, and examine whatever shall be proposed to you, concerning a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain secret Enterprize, that it may be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on and effected to our service, and best advantage; and that you dispose of all things in the best manner for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passing it, making choice of the fittest persons for it; and that you give order for all Boats, Provisions, Furniture of War, and all other necessaries. You shall likewise treat in our Royall Name, and agree upon the rewards and stipends of money, with other advantages for those that shall undertake and effect that thing; and you may engage our Royall Word, for the performance of whatever you contract with them; and so we give you full power and authority, and do promise, and assure you, We will firmly and inviolably observe in all points, whatever shall be particularly agreed upon betwixt you, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41743:36"/> any revocation, because We are so pleased.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Given in</hi> Paris, <hi>Sealed with our sign-Manuel,</hi>
                        <date>
                           <hi>the 5th. of</hi> April <hi>1658.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>And it was Signed LEWIS, and under that, By the King.</hi> Du Tellier.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>These dispatches, which were sent by the <hi>Cardinal</hi> to the Mareshall, were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rge promises, and very fine words, with which his <hi>Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence</hi> did abound, and was very happy in the Art of dis ributing of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m to each man, as a lenitive to his disease: And knowing very well how the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shall's pulse did bear, he told him, that upon the success of this design, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended his advancement, and it would be a chief motive to the King, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre upon him the dignity of Duke and Peer of <hi>France,</hi> and to entail the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of <hi>Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oigne,</hi> with all the <hi>Bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonois</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:41743:37"/> upon him and his sons. This made the Marshall to bestirr his stumps, and to make use of all his five Senses (and more if he had had them) to compasse and bring to perfection this Design, which he found to be no lesse important to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> than convenient for the establishment of his own family. You will see here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after how intricate these deceits were, since <hi>Spintelet,</hi> being solely guided by the dexterity of his <hi>Highness,</hi> was able to cheat the <hi>French,</hi> and to put a slurre upon their Chief <hi>Minister</hi> of State, with the rest of the Councel, who drew-in divers others depending on them.</p>
            <p>These dispatches were brought to the Colonel; of which Copies being taken under pretext of communicating them to the Confederates, they were sent to his <hi>High<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ess</hi> to consider of them, and to let him see that the enemies were in earnest. So by his <hi>Highness</hi> order, the <hi>Mazarinites</hi> were told that all went
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:41743:37"/> well, and that when the Marshall had signed the aforesaid Capitulations, and that they were confirmed by the Kings authority, and as soon as Captain <hi>Spruyt's</hi> Company was come into <hi>Ostend,</hi> they would then without further delay put in execution what was agreed upon, and that there should be a day appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for it. We have form<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rly told you that these Captains were to recruit their Companies to 400. men, so that it was an easie matter to perswade the <hi>Fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch</hi> to bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eve, that those <hi>Courlings,</hi> which were brought into the Town, were the Recruits that had been spoken of, (and, as I take it, the <hi>French</hi> paid the money for the raising them;) which made the jest take so much the better, and the design took the faster root.</p>
            <p>Captain <hi>Spruyt,</hi> some two days after, did actually enter into <hi>Ostend</hi> with his whole Company, which consisted but of eight men: but before he came to the Gates there were about one hundred of these <hi>Courlings</hi> joyned to them, without
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:41743:38"/> either the one or the other knowing upon what accompt. This came present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the ears of these <hi>Cunning Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats,</hi> who likewise had their double Spies under hand that were cheated as well as themselves; for, seeing the recruit to be effectually made, they laid down a sum of money to maintain them, without troubling their heads any further.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>De Bocq</hi> and <hi>Spintelet</hi> perceiving they could now no longer by any artifices deferre the business, having first ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained leave of his <hi>Highness,</hi> did agree with the <hi>Mazarinites,</hi> that the day for action should be the fourth of <hi>May,</hi> in regard that on the third there was an Annuall feast in <hi>Bruges,</hi> upon which day they did with great solemnity ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate the Veneration of the Reliques of the most sacred blood of Christ, which for many ages hath been the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and conservation of that most famous City, having upon frequent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions defended it from eminent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. To this feast there does flock
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:41743:38"/> from all parts a great concourse of people, and among<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t the rest many Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens and Souldiers from the Town of <hi>Ostend;</hi> (who are great lovers of<note n="*" place="margin">Or Faires, which are usual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kept on such days.</note>
               <hi>Kermesses</hi>) whereupon the Town would be the thinner, and they were like to meet with less rubs in their way. The <hi>Mazarinites</hi> found the time and opportunity of this Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day much to their purpose; and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to it, leaving it fully resolved upon, one of them went to give the Marshall notice of it, that he might sign the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles out of hand, that nothing might be wanting on his part. Councellour <hi>de Bocq</hi> at the same time taking his way for <hi>Brussels,</hi> that his <hi>Highness</hi> might give further order.</p>
            <p>The Marquiss of <hi>Caracena</hi> (seeing the <hi>French</hi> so eagerly bent upon the surprisal of <hi>Ostend</hi>) was desirous to take the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage while their minds were upon that, to put a considerable Convoy into <hi>Grave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> &amp; not being in a readines<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to do it,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:41743:39"/> he was very willing to have the business put off, till the eleventh of the said month; but it was a difficult thing to find out new pretexts, without giving a jealousie to the Marshall, who had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared all things in readiness to be on the third in the Rode before <hi>Ostend,</hi> where accordingly he did arrive. Upon which there was spread a rumour over all the Country, that he had an intention to fall upon <hi>Flanders;</hi> some said upon <hi>Ostend,</hi> others upon <hi>Newport,</hi> others upon the <hi>North-forts;</hi> some said, 'Twas only a blind (their design lying upon <hi>Henault</hi> and <hi>Artois</hi>) to draw away the Troops from thence into <hi>Flanders;</hi> in fine, every one shot his bolt at pleasure. Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant Major General <hi>Campi</hi> gave notice immediatly to the other States of the Provinces of the certainty of the news, to the end that (t ll such time as his <hi>Highness</hi> could take further order) they might provide against the danger with all speed; and they sent him 200. men more to perform their part.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:41743:39"/>
            <p>Councellour <hi>de Bocq</hi> met accidental<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with a Son of Colonel <hi>Spintelet</hi>'s, and so (to gain such time as the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisse desired) he wrote another letter from <hi>Ostend,</hi> in the name of the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates, dispatching away the Youth with it as far as <hi>Gaunt</hi> to the said <hi>Spin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telet;</hi> by which he advertised him, that the arrival of the Mareshall in the Rode of <hi>Ostend</hi> had alarum'd all the Country; and that there being foot and horse in the Country, designed for a Convoy to <hi>Graveling,</hi> they had put 400. foot, and a troop of horse into the Town; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Marquisse should not advance too forward, lest he might destroy the business; but that he should rather put off to Sea, upon which they would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly march forth about the 10th. or 11th. of the Month, and that then he should have notice when he might ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect what they all so much desired.</p>
            <p>These Letters were carried (with what possible speed the Colonel's Son could make) to <hi>Sluce;</hi> where, with
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:41743:40"/> much importunity he pressed the <hi>French-men,</hi> that one of them would go away to the Mareshall, to perswade him to agree to it, since all was done for the greater caution; and, since the lives and fortunes of the Confederates depended on it, they besought him that he would have patience, and not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy the business for two or three dayes time, but that he would be pleased to trust to them.</p>
            <p>The Mareshall was easily carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with these apparent reasons, upon the arrivall of this crafty companion, who of his own accord added much more; whereupon he resolved to put off to Sea for four or five days, till such time as the Souldiers for the Convoy were drawn out of Town. <hi>De Bocq</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned with this news to his <hi>Highness</hi> beseeching him that he would be pleas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to send such forces to <hi>Ostend,</hi> as might be sufficient to receive the Mareshall, and also to catch him in the Mouse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trap.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:41743:40"/>
            <p>The <hi>French,</hi> on their part, had made choice of two very able persons (as they thought) who (with some of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Confederates) were to go into the Town in a disguise, and to lye close in the house of a certain Citizen, whose name it were injustice to conceal, since he hath so well served the King, in this and other occasions; but most particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly as Pay-master to the Naval Army which was entertained in the year 1651, and 1652. for the besieging and taking <hi>Graveling</hi> and <hi>Dunkirk.</hi> This was one <hi>Jaques Uleeshauwer,</hi> Brother-in-law to the said <hi>de Bocq,</hi> who harboured and entertained them, and passed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them for a chief Mutineer.</p>
            <p>The Principal of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>se two <hi>French-men</hi> was called <hi>Monet de Joly,</hi> born at <hi>Calais,</hi> who had been a Captain of horse, but at present s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in the <hi>Cardinal</hi>'s Guards; he was a man of parts, and undoubtedly well qualified, had he not had a touch of the ordinary <hi>French</hi> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, and that his want of years made
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:41743:41"/> him over-confident: The other was named <hi>de Fontene,</hi> who either was (or pretended to be) an Ingeniere, but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise one of a very mean capacity, and somewhat deaffish. This man came as deputy to <hi>Monet;</hi> and their Commission was to treat with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates of whatever was to be acted upon the place, to dispose the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shall's entrance into the Town, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stribute his forces, and with the 400. men (which they conceived they had in Town at their own devotion) to pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sess the principal Gates, the main Guards, and the Magazins; to take or kill the Governour, to give the Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word, and what else was to be done; and that then, one of them should re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the Mareshall, with a particular relation, that he might know how to proceed with security.</p>
            <p>These two, above-mentioned, left <hi>Zealand</hi> on the eighth of <hi>May,</hi> taking leave of the other Agents, in Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the said Colonel; and Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:41743:41"/>
               <hi>de Bocq,</hi> came from <hi>Sluce</hi> by the Sea Coast to <hi>Ostend,</hi> in a Wagon, which was purposely provided for them, by one <hi>Robert Mulebeq,</hi> a man of Credit and Estate, a principal Privateer in <hi>Ostend,</hi> whom they also took to be one of the Confederates. Coming near to the Ferry-boat, <hi>de Bocq</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced, upon pretence to see if the Coast were clear, fearing lest they should ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentally stumble upon the Governour in their way, for it was not convenient they should see him or know him; and, to confirm the Cheat the more, the Governour (having notice of their coming) had placed a reformed En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign (who had his lesson without book) as Sentinel, to startle them that they might not seem to be negligent in their Guards; and so being questioned upon their coming out of the Ferry-boat, who they were, and whither they went, 'twas answered by <hi>de Bocq</hi> and <hi>Mule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becq,</hi> that they were <hi>Holland</hi> Marchants, and that they would be answerable for
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:41743:42"/> them. Thus they pass'd the first en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with no small fright; and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the house of the said <hi>Uleeshauwer,</hi> thinking themselves now in Sanctuary, they fell down on their knees, and gave God thanks, that they had so happily escaped out of the hands of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now come I again to act my part of this Comedy, having not been upon the Stage, since the imprisonment of <hi>Spin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telet,</hi> who left me fully instructed in all the Plot. His <hi>Highness</hi> and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiss of <hi>Caracena,</hi> had designed me the person whom the <hi>French</hi> were to seize upon as Governour, in conformity to the agreement betwixt the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, who were to deliver up the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour dead or alive. I being upon the seventh of the same month at <hi>Brus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sells</hi> (deputed by the Country upon some publique imployment) was sent for by his <hi>Excellency</hi> about e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>even of the clock at night, after I was retired to my Chamber, and commanded from his
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:41743:42"/>
               <hi>Highness</hi> to hasten away to <hi>Ostend,</hi> to assist the Governour upon any occasion; for that it would be very grateful to his <hi>Highness,</hi> the Governour much desiring to have me as an assistant to him in this Action.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Excellency</hi> (to prevent my reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or excusing my self from the jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney) did purposely conceal from me the business which I had there to do; but I, who never stuck at any thing, which was commanded me, in relation to his Majesties service (although it were out of the Sphaere of my activi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) offered my self immediately to go away that very night; his <hi>Excellency</hi> giving me a paper, which contained his <hi>Highnesse</hi>'s Commands to that effect, with a letter to the Governour, that he might understand so much; and thus, with a ticket to have the Gates of the Town opened, his <hi>Excellence</hi> dispatch'd me away at Midnight. It was about two hours ere my Boots and Horses were ready, so that before I got two
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:41743:43"/> leagues and a half from <hi>Brussells</hi> it was broad day, and coming very early into <hi>Gant,</hi> 'twas impossible for me to get horses, in regard there was a great Fair that day: Wherefore having no better means to advance, I took a little Boat upon the Channel of <hi>Bruges,</hi> capable to receive about a dozen or fifteen Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ketteers (being one of those in which the <hi>Spanish</hi> foot had pass'd with Serjeant Major <hi>Sanpayo</hi> to <hi>Bruges</hi>) and taking a fresh horse at the half way, I lost but little time, although I feared I should for want of horses. At <hi>Bruges</hi> Gates I met with the said Serjeant Major, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting the arrival of Boats and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, for to continue his journey to <hi>Ostend.</hi> I endeavouring to speak with him, found him at first very reserved, being unwilling to acquaint me with his march, or let me know, that the order he had was not in those express and usuall terms, that were requisite to make him be furnished with convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to passe his men; but discoursing
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:41743:43"/> betwixt our selves, we declared the march to be of Concern; and therefore we resolved, that he should make for <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finguen,</hi> and send his Adjutant with me to <hi>Ostend,</hi> whence the Governour should send further directions what was to be done. I provided him Boats and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visions, and in pursuance of an order from his <hi>Excellency,</hi> I sent the Count <hi>de Grimbergh</hi>'s Troop which lay in Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son at <hi>Bruges,</hi> to <hi>Blanquenbergh,</hi> with directions to observe what orders should be sent them by the Governour of <hi>Ostend;</hi> and so I took Horses, and went away on my journey thither. At the mouth of the Haven I met two of the <hi>Eschevins</hi> of the <hi>Franc,</hi> who were sent by their Magistrates to make provision for the Troops which came in from all parts, no body knowing upon what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, unless it were to make a Convoy for <hi>Graveling.</hi> I thought good to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vise them, that it did much import his Majesties service, that they should quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter close, and not straggle about the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:41743:44"/> Country; for upon that depended the good or ill success of a Design in hand, wherefore they should be very carefull not to commit any disorders in the Country.</p>
            <p>Having made some little stay about this business, and Sailing towards the <hi>Ferry,</hi> whom should I espy upon the Wharfe, but Monsieur <hi>de Mulebesq, Spintelet,</hi> and Counsellour <hi>de Bocq,</hi> who were going to introduce the two <hi>French-men,</hi> before mentioned, into the Town, as 'twas agreed upon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, which I understood by the letters shewed me by the Marquisse of <hi>Caracena;</hi> so that I was forced to delay some time upon the water, to avoid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing seen and known.</p>
            <p>The Governour received me with his wonted civility, as the profest friendship betwixt us might deserve, and with somewhat more than an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary demonstration for the confidence he always had in me; having pass'd some complements, we retired with the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:41743:44"/> Serjeant Major <hi>Don Diego de Herreras</hi> and Counsellour <hi>de Bocq,</hi> to debate about the main business; and being shut up together, the Governour made a formall discourse, with great dissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation commending the zeal and fervour which I had always shewn in his Majesties servic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lling me, how that his <hi>Highness,</hi> and the Marquiss of <hi>Caracena,</hi> had ordered him, in recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of my services, to deliver up t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e government of <hi>Ostend</hi> into my hands, offering me (as an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arnest of it) hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Commanding Cane, which he had in his hand, charging the Serjeant Majo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to obey such orders, as I should give him in the quality of Governour; and all of them together, without expecting my reply, saluted me, and gave me joy. Although I could not but smile at their fained complement, which in it self was so extravagant and remote, yet I was very curious to know what this would amount to at last, and desiring them to leave their drolling, they began
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:41743:45"/> by degrees to explain themselves, and to declare to me, that it was agreed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Confederates and the <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> that they should take the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the place Prisoner, and that his <hi>Highness</hi> and his <hi>Excellence</hi> had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded me to personate him, and that no body could perform it with more dexterity and addresse than my self; so that I had nothing further to reply, for they knew it was not my custome to dispute commands, especially in such an Exigent as that.</p>
            <p>I must confess, that as the preamble of the Governour's discourse made me laugh, who (with his formall gravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was resolved to recreate himself up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my score, to see how I would take it) so was I much surprised at the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion, which was attended with the condition of so chimerical and perilous a government; which you may easily believe, especially, when a proposition is made to an honest man, to counterfeit another mans person: However, seeing it
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:41743:45"/> was upon so extraordinary a piece of service, lest it might be thought I ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wanted resolution, or a will, who upon all other occasions had shew'd my self so forward; without any other consideration than the King's Serv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce, I presently accepted that imaginary go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and resolv'd to do whatever they deemed most expedient, for the carrying on the intended design.</p>
            <p>Whereupon it was resolved that I should make choice of my own Prison, where I thought good. But sett ng aside what might concern that business, we fell into debate concerning the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses of those two <hi>French-men</hi> which were brought in, who had declared that in those Ships and Vessells which lay before the Haven, there were double the number of men agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which they very well observing, all of them, found that those who were sent to re-inforce them, were not suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to secure the place; so they agreed upon dispatching away a Post imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:41743:46"/> to his <hi>Highness,</hi> and to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiss of <hi>Caracena,</hi> that they would please to send them more men that they might be able to receive their enemies without danger.</p>
            <p>And, to disguise this delay to the <hi>French-men,</hi> as also to allay the impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Marquiss (who was at sea) and to keep him from going away, they were made believe, 'twas necessary to deferre the execution for a day or two, because those Troops, designed for a Convoy to <hi>Graveling</hi> (which quartered upon the <hi>Franc</hi> Country) were to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a certain allowance, and so for the ease of the Country-people they were to quarter in the Towns; that this could not hold above two days, and that 'twas very convenient the Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shall should be advertiz'd of it, that he might know it was deferred but the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to secure the success.</p>
            <p>And that they might not think it an excuse, or an invention, it was ordered that the <hi>Spanish</hi> Foot, which lay already
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:41743:46"/> in <hi>Lefinguen,</hi> should be brought into the Town, and should passe through that very street where those two <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> might (by peeping out of their Windows) both see and number them, and that the Marshall might likewise have a view of them as they marched along the Shoar. All this was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd to a tittle; and moreover, I placed my self over against the <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men's</hi> Windows, with the Serjeant Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor of the Town, and two or three Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants in the Governours Livery, where the Captains of the <hi>Spanish</hi> Infantry, who came into the Town, saluted me as they passed by, being my friends and acquaintance; and several of them speaking to me, those two <hi>French-men</hi> which were shut up, asked who we were? And Councellour <hi>de Bocq,</hi> who was with them at their Window, told them, It was the Governour, and the Serjeant Major of the place, describing us by the cloaths we wore; whereupon they (making themselves sure of their
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:41743:47"/> prize) said one to the other, Little think those Gentlemen what will become of them within these 24. hours.</p>
            <p>There remain'd one difficulty, which was, to find out a person to carry this Advise to the Mareshall, some one that was rational, whom they might trust in so important a business: There oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curr'd to my memory one <hi>John Duey,</hi> who (having forfeited his life upon some high mis-demeanours which he had committed) was condemned to be banished. This man was promis'd his pardon, if he would undertake the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying of this message; he accepting of it, the two <hi>French-men,</hi> who were shut up, wrote to the Mareshall all what hath been related, in the most ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacious manner they could; beseech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his <hi>Excellency,</hi> that he would not think the time tedious, since all things went to his hearts desire. This Messenger took a Horse, and made great haste to <hi>Sluce,</hi> from whence in a Boat with Sails and Oars, he soon got on Bord the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:41743:47"/> Mareshall, to whom he delivered his Message to the full. He was so well received and entertained, that he had his answer in a moment, and he being a very Divell of Hell, was hugg'd and kiss'd by the Mareshall himself, who discharging two peeces of Ordnances, gave notice he had received the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch, and likewise, to let them under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, he would willingly wait. He shewed unto this <hi>John Duey</hi> a Chest, which he said was full of double Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolls, to be distributed amongst the Confederate Souldiers; and told him he should not be out of patience, though he were to expect whole years, that he doubted not of their fidelity, and that he might assure them so much. <hi>Duey</hi> had purposely ordered his Horse to be sent back to <hi>Blanquenbergh,</hi> which is the half way betwixt <hi>Ostend</hi> and <hi>Sluce,</hi> and in his return he was set on shore there, so that his diligence seemed miraculous.</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:41743:48"/>
            <p>In the mean time, I thought it good to find out persons to manage my im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisonment, and such as I might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fide in, for so important a business. There were two Companies of Auxilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the <hi>Count de Meghems Tercia,</hi> under Captain <hi>Eguels,</hi> and Captain <hi>Febre:</hi> These as my friends and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance (having first taken their Words and Oaths of secresie) I thought best to instruct, and to make them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments in carrying on that matter, so by degrees I began to acquaint them with the principal design, as likewise to inform them what they were to do in particular, and by what means they should be introduced into the company and acquaintance of those <hi>French</hi> Spyes that were shut up, and the other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Conspirators. These, feigning themselves to be reformed-Officers, that had taken a discontent, for having been affronted by the Governour, and had vowed revenge, were call'd by Councellor <hi>de Bocq</hi> into the presence of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:41743:48"/> these two <hi>French-men,</hi> as friends and relations of Colonel <hi>Spintelet,</hi> who were resolved to steer his course, and run the same fortune with him, ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing their miserable lives, which they said were a burthen to them, so much were they oppressed by the many inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries they had received from the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</p>
            <p>They were received with open arms into the Committy, and there they fell presently to debate (according to the instructions I had given them) whether it were best to kill the Governour, or to take him prisoner. One alleadged, that the chief person in command being dead, there would certainly want the necessary Orders, and so in case they should endeavour to make a head, and to rally, they would never be able to give any considerable opposition; that it was to be feared so great a Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion could not be without Tumult and hurly-burly; and having removed out of the way the principal persons, who
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:41743:49"/> were most to be feared, all would be safe.</p>
            <p>The other, on the contrary, urg'd that the Governour, in the present po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture the Town was in, could not get together three men; besides, although what the other alleadged should fall out, yet keeping him well-guarded, neither of them could want a dagger to take another resolution; and that it was not probable that either the <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Cardinal</hi> would refuse a Prisoner to those two Gentlemen, who had ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured themselves upon the place, which was the least recompence he could give them; and that he knew for certain, that he had 80000. <hi>Ducats</hi> ready Cash in <hi>Bruges,</hi> which was an infallible Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some, much more to be valued than his <hi>Carkasse;</hi> and, grant it should not be given them, yet such a summe of money might serve at any time to fortifie the <hi>Sasse</hi> of <hi>Plasquendal,</hi> by which means, all the land about it would be their own; that to expect money from
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:41743:49"/>
               <hi>France,</hi> would require some weeks time, which were to give the <hi>Spaniard</hi>'s leisure to come and fortifie themselves there, and consequently to render <hi>Ostend</hi> uselesse to the most Christian King.</p>
            <p>These Reasons (together with the news of the money, of which they thought themselves sure) made the <hi>French-men</hi> begin to unlock their five Senses, and having heard all their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, the most being for the killing of the Governour &amp; (all this, as I told you, in order to the Instructions I had given them) the two <hi>French-men</hi> declared ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely for the negative, giving express Order, that they should by no means kill him, repeating many times, <hi>Non mordieu il ne faut pas le tuer,</hi> but that they should let him live and use him well, and fish the<note n="*" place="margin">Or Double Pistolls.</note>
               <hi>Doblons</hi> out of him, and after they had resolved upon this point each man retired to his Chamber.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:41743:50"/>
            <p>All this passed upon the eleventh of <hi>May,</hi> his <hi>Excellence</hi> having already given Command, that to the <hi>Spanish</hi> Foot should be added the <hi>Count de Megems</hi> whole <hi>Tercia,</hi> and the Regiment of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>'s, of <hi>Don Alberto Coloma,</hi> writing to the Governour, that with this strength, there was nothing to be feared.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Excellency</hi>'s Letters and his Troops arrived not till the thirteenth in the morning, for they were commanded to make a halt at <hi>Lefinguen,</hi> till they had setled other matters. The first thing that was to be done, was to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch a second Messenger to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shall, to let him know that the Troops would march out of Town that very thirteenth day, to the end, that he should prepare to fall in with the Tyde on the fourteenth, being the day follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and about eleven of the clock at night they sent away the same <hi>John Duey</hi> a second time, to let him know that the Convoy was in a readiness to go out; that they would march the next
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:41743:50"/> day without fail, and that they might discover them from Sea, and by a white cloth, which should at the same time be held up in a Mans hand, upon the great Bullwark of the Haven; and that he would please to signifie to them, by dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging of two Guns, and by hanging out a White-flag upon the Stern of his Ship, whether he was resolved to come and second them.</p>
            <p>All this succeeded to wish, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shall having given the Signall with two piece of Ordnance, and the White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>streamer; The Governour command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Drums to beat up, and the <hi>Spanish</hi> Foot to march out the same way that they had taken; and I, placing my self directly over against them in the same equipage, was taken notice of again, that they might not mistake me the night following. Serjeant Major <hi>Sanpayo</hi> had order, that as he passed along the Sands, about a league off from the Town, he should crosse over the Downs, and make a halt, calling to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:41743:51"/> him the other two Regiments which were in <hi>Lefinguen,</hi> with express order that upon pain of death no man should appear upon the Downs, to be discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by those at Sea; and for greater security, they planted Sentinells, and the Officers themselves had strict charge to prevent it.</p>
            <p>All this was a Riddle to both Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Souldiers, who could not guess to what all this caution tended. 'Tis not to be expressed what joy there was amongst the <hi>French-men,</hi> as well those two who lay privately in the Town, as also those who were in the Ships; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the one or the other were able to contain themseles, they were so puft up with the hopes of being Masters of so important a place within few hours; being Eye-witnesses of the marching away of those who obstructed their Conquest, and counted their very Ranks as they marched through the Town; and those on Ship-board were troubled at nothing more, than that they had not
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:41743:51"/> Perspective-glasses to do the same upon the Shore.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Spanish</hi> Foot having marcht out, and the rest of them being come to <hi>Lefinguen,</hi> with the Cavalry which were expected, it was thought requisit to recommend the good success to his Divine Majesty, the Supreame Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductour of humane affairs, on whom depends the good or evil events of all enterprizes; whereupon a solemn Masse was order'd to be said in the great Church, none knowing upon what occasion, only to implore the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine assistance for his Majesties good success, to which were invited the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates, together with the chief of the Souldiery and Towns-men, and it was recommended to the Guardian of the <hi>Capuchins</hi> to order the devotions of his Convent to the same intent.</p>
            <p>Having thus performed the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of highest Concern, the Governour caused an assembly of the Magistrates, being attended on by <hi>de Bocq</hi> and my
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:41743:52"/> self; When we had taken our seats, the doors being barr'd, I told them the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour had a business to propound to them, of so great importance to his Majesties service, that before it were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to them, they must first be all sworn by the Bayliffe to keep secresie with all strictness, it being so absolutely essential, that without it all would fall to the ground; and an Oath being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly tendred to them in due form, Councellour <hi>de Bocq</hi> began a large and ample discourse, relating to them the whole business from the beginning, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring their concurrence, and assistance in accomplishing the work. They very readily offered themselves to do what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever should be ordered them; so it was agreed upon, that after the Gates were shut, they should divide themselves into every street and quarter of the Town, by two and two; and that they should speak with every family, charging them, that whatever Rumour they should hear, that Night after Mid-night, or
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:41743:52"/> about break of day, that not a man of them should stir, nor open a Door or Window, although they should hear the Cannons to play, the <hi>French</hi> Drums to beat, and the people to cry, <hi>Vive la France:</hi> However that each man should have his Fire-arms ready fixt, that when they should hear the jangling o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Bells, every man should then repair to his Colours, to go where-ever they should be appointed, and that they should fear nothing, since all was for the good of the Town. In the second place, he told them how the two <hi>French-men</hi> were shut up, and that the night being come, and the counterfeit-Governour secured, it was agreed upon by the pretended Conspiratours, the better to wheedle the <hi>French-men,</hi> that in that interim, whilst they expected the coming in of the Tide, they should as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble the Magistrates, and propound to them the swearing of <hi>Fealty</hi> to the King of <hi>France,</hi> wherefore he wished them to carry it so, as that some should
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:41743:53"/> pretend to retreat out of Town; others, that they would not swear; some, that they would; however, that they should order it, in such manner, that there might be an equality of votes, so that nothing should be concluded on; allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging they were not sufficiently im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owered from the King to tender them such an Oath, and that the matter should rest undecided, and be deferred till the arrival of the Mareshall. That Serjeant Major <hi>Don Diego de Herrera</hi> should be ready at the place of Armes, to conduct the <hi>Burgers</hi> to that part of the Walls which they were to defend, where they should receive farther or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            <p>Having given them this admonition, we took our leaves of the Magistrates, and went to the Covent of the <hi>Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chins,</hi> advising the Guardian in general terms, that they should keep quiet and still whatever they heard; and that they should prepare their Church, to shelter the <hi>Count de Meghem's Tercia</hi> of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:41743:53"/>
               <hi>Wallone</hi> Foot, appointing some one to open and shut their Gate, betwixt nine and ten of the clock at night. There was the same care taken with the <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torian</hi> Fathers, the Pastors of the great Church, that they should receive-in the <hi>Spanish</hi> and <hi>Alman</hi> Infantry, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted to some 1200. men; and, this done, we went to eat, as if no such thing had been to follow.</p>
            <p>We passed the evening in ordering who should command the Artillery and dispose the Batteries, and for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose they appointed the Captains and Masters of Ships, with such Sea-men as were in Town. There was another in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention found out for the greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion of those who were to be let into the Town, which was to clap up some ten or twelve men in Prison, giving the Keeper private notice, that at Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, when he should see the <hi>French-men</hi> enter with Colonel <hi>Spintelet, de Bocq,</hi> and others, to demand the Keys; he should then let out those ten or
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:41743:54"/> twelve men, with some <hi>English</hi> Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which were taken some few days before; but if he had any criminal Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soners, or that were considerable, he should shut them up where they should not be seen; and I, on the other side, entertain'd my self with running over the lessons of those who were to take me Prisoner, that every one being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in his part, might act it to the life. The Officers of Horse and Foot were sent for to Town by an Adjutant; the Horse were ordered to march, and be before Mid-night (300. of them with their Serjeant Majors, the Baron <hi>de Courieres,</hi> and Monsieur <hi>Voglaer</hi>) on that part of the Downs which is call'd <hi>Lissemorre,</hi> whither they should be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted by Monsieur <hi>le Fabre,</hi> one of the <hi>Eschevins</hi> of the <hi>Franc,</hi> and that Serje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Major <hi>de Feu,</hi> with 150. more, should come by the Bank of <hi>Plasquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal,</hi> to plant themselves behind it, at the point which is towards the Haven called <hi>Slicque,</hi> whither they should be
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:41743:54"/> guided by Monsieur <hi>de Maldegem,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Eschevin</hi> of the <hi>Franc;</hi> and that being come to their Posts, they should alight, not quitting the Bridle out of their hands; and, upon pain of death, that they should not straggle, much less shew themselves upon the Downs, or on the Banke, nor to get on Horse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back, till such time as they heard the Muskets play from the Walls of the Town.</p>
            <p>The Foot were charged not to stir from the place where they were, till late at night, and, that then, without beat of Drum, or Match lighted, they should march to the Town, where they should find the Gates open, and one to conduct them under the Walls to the Church, or to that part where they were to be shut up, from whence (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever should happen, either noise of Drums or Cannons) they were not to move, untill such time the Governour should direct them what to do. These orders being given out, each man reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:41743:55"/> to act what was assigned him: They had caution given them, not to permit any living soul to go out of the Gates, lest the secret should be discovered, which was a kind of Miracle, since there was a necessity it should passe through the hands of so many, and so different persons.</p>
            <p>It being now night, the Governour, the Serjeant Major, and my self, went to open the Gates to let in the Foot, each one guiding his party: The first led the <hi>Spanish</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oot under the Walls on the right-hand, towards the great Church; the Serjeant Major led the <hi>Germans</hi> the same way; and I with the <hi>Walloons</hi> passed under the Walls of the<note n="*" place="margin">Water Piles.</note>
               <hi>Cofres,</hi> to shut them up in the <hi>Capuchins</hi> Church, where they all remained, without know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng what work was in hand, or in what they were to be employed. I told them the same thing which I had told the Gardian, and that I would be with them again about two or three of the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:41743:55"/> clock in the morning, and that then I would conduct them where they were to continue for some time.</p>
            <p>There fell out an unexpected Accident about this time, which was like to have disordered the whole Design; which being in it self so frivolous, it is worth a man's observation to consider, How small a matter may serve to dash such enterprizes. Thus it was; the Camp-boys who attended the <hi>Spanish</hi> Infantry, and other Servants with their Master's Led-horses, running up and down the streets to seek their Quarters, did make such a hurly-bury, that they alarum'd the two <hi>French-men;</hi> which being observed by the Master of the house, and the rest who were at Supper, to divert it, they, under pretence of beginning a health, made such a dinn with their Knives and Dishes, that they no more minded what the business was; which really was a great presence of mind in such an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion. They told them, that the Governor with other Officers, were returned from
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:41743:56"/> seeing the Troops march with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy towards <hi>Gravelin;</hi> so their appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension being over, they continued their Drinking of Healths to the most Christian <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Cardinal,</hi> the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shall,</hi> and to their good success; of which they made no doubt.</p>
            <p>We (having made all things sure) went to the Governour's house, where we Supp't at our leasure, smiling and pleasing our selves with the expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the good day following, which was the 14. of <hi>May.</hi> Supper being ended in good conversation, I retired to a Chamber, where there lay ready a Box with the Keys of the Town and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazins, several Papers upon the Table, &amp; a Desk to write upon; and you must know, there was only a little Court of the House, to be cross'd to these Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, so that one might go to them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any noise or disturbance. They all retired to take a little rest, and to make themselves ready to act their parts, which were to begin precisely at Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:41743:56"/> I being now in my quarters, and having already put on the Order of <hi>St. Jago,</hi> flinging the Governour's Cloak over my shoulders, with the same badge; I had nothing further to do but to School a Laquay of the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour's, who lay at my Beds-feet upon a Mattresse, and knew nothing of what was in hand; I wish'd him only to make a counterfeit bus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le, telling him that those that were to rush in to take me prisoner, were friends, and of his acquaintance in the Town, so that he need fear nothing, but that he should dissemble the best he could, but so as not to disturb or destroy the work. I reflected with my self, that one of these <hi>French-men</hi> (when they should see me hold up the dispute at that height) might happen to give me a stab, or prick me in some part of the body, that could not brook cold Iron, either upon my violent crying out, or upon any slight occasion; wherefore I took a quire of paper, and opening it, I clapt it
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:41743:57"/> to the mouth of my Stomack, and upon some part of my Belly, which I thought might be proff against a thrust, in case it should come to triall, or that the <hi>Monsieur</hi> should have a mind to pink my Doublet. Into one of my Pockets I slipt a Pistoll, and into the other a Poniard or <hi>Stiletto,</hi> of those which they had hid in a private place, to be distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted amongst the Conspirators.</p>
            <p>In this Posture (far from shutting my eyes) I for the space of an hour, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected their coming to take me, which I knew was to be precisely about Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night. The clock had no sooner struck, but ere you could say a <hi>Miserere,</hi> I could hear them advancing, <hi>cum la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternis, facibus, &amp; armis,</hi> making a great noise upon their surprising t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Sentinel, which is usually set at the Governour's door, where there was at this time placed by design a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed<note n="*" place="margin">An Officer which in the <hi>Spanish</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantry is both En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign and Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</note>
               <hi>Alferez,</hi> who had no need to be taught his lesson. They now
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:41743:57"/> began their Action of battery against my Chamber-door, and with their Hammers and Iron-barrs, they opened it, in a less space than was requisite for the waking of me though I had slept never so soundly. They came rushing into my Chamber in a crowd, and two of the Captains seizing upon me, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeited so much to the life, that they had almost choaked me, so that being scarce able to breathe, I could not arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate with my voice, what I seemed desirous to express; it came at last to be past dissembling, for they had so throatled me with a Linnen-cloath, or Cravat, which I had about my neck, that (had it continued but a little long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er) there had been an end of my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeiting; and my <hi>French Monsieur</hi>'s bad been defeated of their Ransome, with which they were so much tickled. At last, the chief of those two <hi>French-men,</hi> call'd <hi>Du Monet,</hi> he that was Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Horse in the <hi>Cardinal</hi>'s Guards, whith his Sword in his hand, spoke thus
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:41743:58"/> unto me: Submit your self to the Arms of <hi>France,</hi> for the Town is the King's, the Mareshall <hi>D' Aumont</hi> is at the Gates ready to enter, I have taken pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session of it in his name, the People and the Garrison have declared for the most Christian King. By this time, I was a little come to my self, and feigning to be infinitely troubled, I cry'd out in Spanish, <hi>Arma, Arma, sargento Major, traycion, traycion;</hi> making as if I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood not what he said to me: and, when I espied Colonel <hi>Spintelet</hi> amongst them, I addressed my complaints to him, calling him Infamous Traytor, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him I never expected better of him, and raging like a Mad-man out of his wits, I begg'd of them to kill me, making as if I would have snatch'd one of their Swords out of their hands: In fine, I dissembled as much as it was pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, endeavouring to expresse great rage and indignation, from which in reallity I was free enough. <hi>Du Monet,</hi> (seeing me so highly afflicted, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>composed,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:41743:58"/> reflecting perchance on the 80000. <hi>ducats,</hi> which I had not at <hi>Bruges</hi>) endeavouring all he could to comfort me, with much gallantry, and fine language, he said, Sir, you must please to suffer the Crosses of Fortune with a generous spirit; remembring who you are, and the great valour which you have for so many years shewn in your King's service; this was a Stratagem of War, from which the greatest Commanders are not secure; you are betray'd by your own men, and against such treason there is no defence; your reputation is so established in the Army, that you can never suffer in it, your courage is too well known; the affairs of War have their ebbs and flows, and what is held to be most se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, is often lost in an hour: Comfort your self, Sir, with this, the King of <hi>France</hi> is a mighty Monarch, and the Mareshall a noble Lord, He will both give you good Quarter, and use your Lady with all Civillity; Resolve to bear
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:41743:59"/> this mis-fortune like a man of courage, and conform your self to time and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion. As well he might have spoken all that while to a Wall, for I made as if I understood him not, still talking on like a Mad-man; with that my <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur</hi> began to take Pepper in the Nose, and said in great wroth, Bid him hold his tongue, and be quiet, or, I will clap my Sword in his Guts; which crabbed Logick sounded harsh in my ears, whereupon I put my hand in my Pock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, keeping my eye upon him, to see if he persisted in such Blasphemy,; if he had, I should have made bold to have sing'd his Beard for him; <hi>Sed motos praestat componere fluctus,</hi> but I thought it best to furle up my Sails, the high winds of my passion seeming to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed; so I expressed the anguish and trouble I seem'd to have in my mind, only by sighing and sobbing.</p>
            <p>As they led me along, we passed by the <hi>Capuchins</hi> Church, where the Count <hi>de Meghem</hi>'s Regiment was shut vp, and
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:41743:59"/> so to the little Market-place, to meet with Captain <hi>Hornes,</hi> who, with a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred men ready in Arms (which by agreement he had got together upon the discharging a Pistol) march'd all in good order, to seize upon the Court of Guards at the Gate of the <hi>Cay;</hi> and being come within fifty paces of them, he sent a Serjeant Major with a Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard of twenty five Muskettiers, to fall in amongst those careless Souldiers, who having but one Sentinel and six or seven old men, hovering over a little fire, and three or four more asleep, it was an easie matter for them to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge some few Muskets in the air, and two or three of them to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit being hurt, besmearing themselves with a little blood, which they had pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posely provided. These were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the said <hi>Monsieur du Monet</hi> to be sent away to the Hospital; the rest were disarmed; and he told them very courteously in <hi>Italian,</hi> as well as he could, <hi>Figlivoli bon animo è fortuna de la Guerra
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:41743:60"/> hauretè bon quartiere.</hi> He delivered me up to that Court of Guard, with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse charge to Captain <hi>Febre,</hi> to keep me safe: As for Captain <hi>Eguel's,</hi> I had before given him order not to stir an Inch from <hi>du Monet,</hi> but strictly to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve his words and actions, and to squeeze out of him what possible he could of the design of these Gentlemen, and what they farther intended, having possessed themselves of so important a place: Nor was the Captain careless to do so, to whom this <hi>French-man</hi> had already promised to be instantly put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Command of a Company in the Regiment of <hi>Picardy.</hi> In the interim, they met with great difficulty in open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Gates: for, the usual Porter not being prepared for it, and much surpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to see the Town surrendred, in that confusion had mingled his Keys toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, so that they were forced to send for a <hi>Spanish</hi> Corporal from the Court of Guard to open them; who patiently bore some Raps of the Pate,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:41743:60"/> the better to disguise his trouble.</p>
            <p>The Gates being opened, Colonel <hi>Spintelet,</hi> and Advocate <hi>de Bocq</hi> (who, as I said before, went by the name of <hi>Stapin</hi>) told them, that now they had nothing further to do on their part, and that the rest did not depend on them; wherefore the Souldiers began to cry, <hi>Spintelet, Spintelet,</hi> Money, Money, Money; to which <hi>du Monet</hi> replyed, Gentlemen, your money is ready in the Ships, the Mareshall brings it with him, and I assure you, you shall have more than was promised you; [and I believe he spake a truth, meaning blows, the usuall rewards of Traytors.]</p>
            <p>At the same time the two Captains, <hi>Sneyers</hi> and <hi>Spruit,</hi> possessed themselves of the Main Guards, and of the Gate of <hi>Newport,</hi> who a little before had had notice given them of what would hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen. Then this <hi>du Monet,</hi> with Captain <hi>Eguels,</hi> the Colonel, and many others of the pretended Conspirators, got) upon the Walls, and changed all the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:41743:61"/> Sentinells, and the Word, which they gave, St. <hi>Lewis.</hi> After that, they went to the grand Battery, whence they did let flie three pieces of Ordnance, as a Signall, to shew they were Masters of the Place; hanging forth a great Sheet upon a Pole, instead of a white Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as they use in <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>English</hi> fleet, which lay in the Rode (having in her the Mareshall, with those men which were to be brought into the Town) answered likewise with three pieces of Cannon; but it being as yet not day, nor the time of Tyde serving, which we had duly weigh'd, <hi>du Monet</hi> resolved to go and assemble the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates, to make them swear Allegiance to the most Christian King. And by the way, as they were going, he told Captain <hi>Eguels,</hi> that there would be suddenly d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s-embark'd a very puissant Army, to conquer the whole Country; and that, leaving <hi>Dunkirk</hi> and <hi>Gravelin</hi> (which of themselves would fall in) they would begin with that which was
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:41743:61"/> the most solid, and essential. First of all, they would Fortifie <hi>Plasquendall,</hi> to command the Water: Then he fell to his ejaculations, crying out to himself, with a loud voice; Oh fortunate King of <hi>France,</hi> now thou art truly a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, since, in one day, I have added to thy Crown so powerful, and rich a Country, which thou hast gain'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the losse of one man! What re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward may not a poor Gentleman expect at thy hands, who with the hazzard of his life, hath made thee Earl of <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders!</hi> Thus did his tongue run riot, entertaining Captain <hi>Eguels</hi> with such extravagant discourses; and, promising to himself mountains of gold, he came to the Town-house, by the way fling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing open the Prison, and letting our those, who were not really imprisoned (as I formerly said) but such as were clapt up by design; telling them that in the King of <hi>France</hi> his Name, he gave them their liberty.</p>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:41743:62"/>
            <p>Some few days before, they had taken five or six <hi>English</hi> Marriners, and those were purposely freed, they which took them losing their ramsomes, which they ought not to have done. This did extreamly confirm them, and heighten their confidence; for the news arriving at the Fleet (being sent thither with the Pilots who went to bring in the <hi>French</hi>) they did there divulge the ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Town.</p>
            <p>There came the Bayliff, Burgoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, and Head-borroughs, running in great hurry, and confusion to the Town-house, some of them half naked, making as if they had been frighted out of their Beds. He made them a large discourse, how that by the just judgment of God, that Place was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the obedience of its lawfull Lord, and natural King, since the most Christian King's Title to those Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, was so clear and manifest, that no body could question it; and that after so many years of slavery, they
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:41743:62"/> might rejoyce to have come back to the obedience of so benigne, and just a Prince; being free'd from the yoke and tyranny of <hi>Spain;</hi> and since they had obtained this grace without toil or blood-shed, he desired them all in his presence, to swear Fidelity to the most Christian King.</p>
            <p>As to this point, they all had their instructions, which were, to debate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst themselves, whether they should swear or not, upon which, being divided in their opinions, they resolved to spur him the question. Whether he were fully empowered (which they well knew he was not) to take their oaths. In case he had, they would have shift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it off upon equality of Votes, desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it might be deferred till the entry of the Mareshall, which would be in a very few hours: Upon hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> answer, that he had no power, the matter for that time was laid aside, they promising to keep together, till they had the honour to see the Mareshall.</p>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:41743:63"/>
            <p>The day now began to break, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about half an hour past one, or up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the point of two of the clock, at which time he gave order, that they should take me from the Court of Guard, and that they should carry me to some Inn, or private house, with a guard of a dozen men, and a Serjeant, giving them a strict charge of my person; but withall, that they should treat me with all civility and courtesie. Whereupon they carried me to a place, not far from the Walls, near unto the <hi>Capuchins.</hi> Then returned he to the Town-house, to order the disposing of the men who were to come in with the Mareshall, for the guarding the several Posts of the place, sending away a relation of all what had pass'd to the Fleet, by his Camarade (who was present at all, and had been shut up with him) and by the Pilots before mentioned, and the <hi>English</hi> who escaped out of Prison, and with a letter of his own. They were not long in carrying their intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence;
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:41743:63"/> for, the Mareshall presently fired three pieces of Cannon, and by the Pendents and Streamers which they hung out, it might plainly be discerned from the Walls, that the <hi>French</hi> thought themselves absolutely Masters of the Place.</p>
            <p>In the interim (leaving my Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man very busie, and writing, as I was told by several persons who observed him) I slipt out of my Prison by a back door; and passing through Narrow-lanes, and little By-alleys, I came to the Governour's house; where we could not but celebrate with laughter, all that had passed. The Governour, and I, (hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing comforted our stomacks with <hi>Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colate</hi>) went upon the Walls, whence we could descry a Shallop, making into the Haven in all haste, Rowing against Tide, which we conceived to be some one sent before to scout, and see, if the Coast were clear; nor were we deceived. The Governour retired privately to his house, and I fair and
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:41743:64"/> softly stept back to my Prison.</p>
            <p>A while after, <hi>du Monet</hi> was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertized there was a Gentleman arrived from the Mareshall; he presently left his business, and ran to receive him with open armes at the <hi>Cay,</hi> he shew'd him the Gates of the Town open, the Keys of the Magazins, the Souldiery crying <hi>viva Francia,</hi> a <hi>Spintelet,</hi> a <hi>Spintelet,</hi> Money, Money; to conclude all, he brought him to see the Governour un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Custody. I being advised of his coming (by my Keepers) did set Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinels at the Street-door, in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, at the Windows, and doubled them upon the Stairs, another at my Chamber-door, and two within, in sight of me, every one of them asking the Word, with extraordinary punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allity, and strictness, which was more and more to encrease the confidence of one who was already sufficiently decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. In fine, in rush'd a crow'd, where I was leaning upon my Elbow sighing, and as melancholy as a Lover's Lute.
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:41743:64"/> The Messenger began, with great Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, to deliver me a Complement from the Marshal, comforting me in my mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, assuring me of good usage, and fair quarter, as well for my own Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, as for my Wife and Children; he told me, that the King was a sufficient gainer by the place, and that, without doubt I should be speedily freed, since I was bought and sold, with a great deal more of such stuff; and whereas he expected a correspondent answer to his complement, I did very soberly (ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king as if I understood him not) ask Captain <hi>Febre</hi> in <hi>Spanish, Que dize, Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nore?</hi> What says he, Sir? He on the other side, labour'd all he could to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate, and interpret his <hi>Harangue,</hi> using, in a manner, the very same words; to which I answered with much gravity, that the Mareshall might do by me as he pleased, I should neither ask, nor take quarter, that I was a lost man on all hands, that I had formerly been his Prisoner, and that I expected
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:41743:65"/> no better usage from him now, that I was taken unarmed, then, when I was taken, in the open field; that he might spare his complements, which I nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther needed, nor regarded; and so I turned my back to him: with which he was so netled, that he used this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression to his companion, and the rest who were present, <hi>Mordieu l'arrogance Espanole!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As he returned to re-imbark himself, passing the Gate, and the Court-guard, the Souldiers still cryed out, a <hi>Spintelet,</hi> a <hi>Spintelet,</hi> Money, Money, Money; with this cry they followed him to his Boat, they Beat their Drums for the morning watch after the <hi>French</hi> Mode, and Beat a <hi>French</hi> March to the Place of Arms, and to the Walls; all the Burgers keeping their Windows and Doors close shut, according to the order given them the night before, by the Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boroughs, as was before mentioned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Du Monet</hi> returned to the Town-house, to finish the disposing of the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:41743:65"/> men for the Guards, which he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun; allotting to some the Market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place, to others the Gates, according to the quality of the Troops. In which employment we will leave him a while; for what follows, will prove Tragicall to him.</p>
            <p>Day coming on apace, it was now time to un-mask, and to shake off our disguise, for we could from the Walls discover the <hi>French</hi> Infantry, shifting out of the great <hi>English</hi> Ships into small <hi>French</hi> Vessels, to get into the Haven, the Tide being within an hour ready to flow. Above all things, we thought it necessary to make sure of this man, and he having taken me Prisoner at Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, I thought I was bound to treat him with the same civility, as he had shewed to me; and to save the life of a man of so much resolution and courage, which in the greatest enemies is always to be valued. At first the Governour, and my self, had thoughts of hanging him up upon a Wind-mill at the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay,</hi> to
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:41743:66"/> undeceive their men; but the great cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and generosity which I observed in the man, made me have a kindness for him; so I resolved to beg his life of his <hi>Highness,</hi> and his <hi>Excellence,</hi> which afterwards I did, and obtained it. So lapping a Skarff about my Middle, with a Pistoll by my Side, not knowing what might happen, I went along with Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Eguels,</hi> and some Souldiers, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend him; I found him Writing of his Orders; and he seeing me come into the Room, with a Skarff and Pistoll, my Staff and Hat in my hand, he started back in an amaze, I made up towards him, and said to him in <hi>French, Monsieur,</hi> what is it you fear? I come not to you with my Sword in my Hand, as you d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d at Mid-night when you took me; I come to bid you welcome, and embrace you in these armes, which have long expected you here: Therefore, Sir, give me leave to tell you, you are welcome; which that you may believe to be reall, I shall need to use no other language
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:41743:66"/> than your own. These are Accidents and Stratagems of War, from which the greatest Souldiers are not secure; have patience, and conform your self to your fortune: for, men of courage, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever falls out, are always themselves, and remain as firm as rocks. Comfort your self with what I shall tell you; you well enough know, Whosoever enters secretly into a Garrison-town, and continuing there shall cause a Revolt, or endeavour to debauch the Garrison, or with-draw the People or Magistrates from the obedience of their lawfull Lord, and natural King, carries his Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence along with him; neither can he expect any quarter, by the laws of War or Nature. Wherefore all things are prepared in a readiness, for the breaking you alive upon the Wheel, to serve as an Example and Terrour to others, lest at any time hereafter they should attempt the like design; however, your civill carriage to me, and the rest of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soners (whom you did really believe in your power) hath so far gained upon
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:41743:67"/> me, that, I assure you, your person shall not be touch'd, and I will cast my self at his <hi>Highnesses</hi> feet, to beg both your life and liberty, which I am confident will not be denied me: In the mean while be of good courage, I here give you my hand to make good my promise, neither shall you want the command of my purse.</p>
            <p>You may well imagine what different effects this discourse of mine did work in this person, and in how great a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion he was, however, he made no reply, but shrinking up his Shoulders, he said, I am young, and inconsiderate. Thus leaving him under the Custody of a Serjeant with half a dozen Souldiers to guard him, I returned to the Walls. At the same time they rung their Bells, the signall (as I said before) for the Towns-men to open their Houses, and to repair with their Armes, each man to his Colours.</p>
            <p>It was about four of the clock, the Tyde beginning to come in, which at ten was to be High-water,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:41743:67"/> when we could perceive all our enemies to be got out of the <hi>English</hi> Ships, and to be embarked in lesser Vessels, Pinna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and other <hi>French</hi> Boats, which they had brought for that purpose from <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lais,;</hi> and whilst they waited the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of the Tyde, they floated about with their Streamers and Pendents, beating their Drums, and playing on their Flutes, as if they were making an Entry of Triumph.</p>
            <p>He, who Commanded in the Town, was not wanting to defend the Walls, with those men which were come in; so he ordered some <hi>Spaniards</hi> to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terscarpe, that lay against the Haven, and the Ferry, since it was apparent they must disembark there; in the <hi>Stone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redout,</hi> which is upon the <hi>Cay,</hi> he placed 30. <hi>Spanish</hi> Muskettiers, which were those who were like to do the best exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, the <hi>Walloons</hi> and <hi>Germans</hi> cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Counterscarpe, from the Sally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port to the Sea-side, and what were over and above were placed upon the Walls; so likewise were the Towns<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:41743:68"/> from the very front of the Dock to <hi>Newport</hi> Gate, with which the Town was so well defended, that it needed not to have feared a whole Army. All the Artillery was man'd with three men to a Gun, and those were Sea-Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and Gunners of the Town. In this posture (the Souldiers falling flat down with their Arms upon the ground, lest they should be discovered from the Top-masts of the Ships) We expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with patience an hour, none but the Governour, and my self, walking upon the Walls, discoursing whether they would enter or not, and after what manner we should receive them, and whether it were best to strike a terrour into them by firing upon them, or else to send out some person to let them know that they were sold, and meerly trapan'd, that therefore they should fling down their Arms, and submit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; otherwise, to their Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, they should find by experience their greater confusion. This was my advice, offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to go out my self, and to acquaint
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:41743:68"/> them in what a Predicament they were, and without doubt they would have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted our offer, which seemed to me the more glorious action; however, the Governour being wiser, and more cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumspect, was resolved to proclaim their confusion to them by a Volley of Shot, lest there might be a treble de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign, as this was double. In fine, he being so great a Souldier, and all being to be filed upon his accompt, my rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons were out of doors.</p>
            <p>In the interim, the Tide began to rise, and ere it was half-flood, we could, to our great satisfaction, discover ten Ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sells, coming in with a North East wind (which was what they desired) loaded w th men; their Arms in their hands, their Banners displayed, with Drums beating, playing on their Flutes, as if they were at a Wedding, with the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broydred Blew-coats of the King's guard of Mu kettiers, and Cardinal <hi>Mazarin</hi>'s Red-coats, with their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in all their gallantry, and the <hi>Marshall</hi> in the midst of them, with
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:41743:69"/> his Order of the Holy Ghost.</p>
            <p>The Wind was so brisk, that having once pass'd the Shelf, at the coming into the Haven, there was no stopping of themselves, by reason of the violent stream, that came along with them, and likewise, in regard of the Wind. In this posture, they came to the <hi>Cay</hi> without, and climbing over the Bilanders, and other Vessells which were there, they came on Shoar, to draw themselves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Squadrons.</p>
            <p>There is one thing not to be forgot: the Mareshall before he came out of the <hi>English</hi> Ship, in which he was, had sent a<note n="*" place="margin">A Pinnace, or nimble Boat.</note>
               <hi>Patache</hi> to the <hi>Cardinal,</hi> with the advice of the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, which he thought he had already got; who with that Wind, which I spoke of, got in few hours to <hi>Calais,</hi> to the Count <hi>de Charon,</hi> who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently dispatch't away a Gentleman Post to the <hi>Cardinal,</hi> giving him joy of the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Ostend,</hi> and by consequence all <hi>Flanders;</hi> the <hi>Cardinal</hi> did not omit to send away with all speed to <hi>Frankfort,</hi>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:41743:69"/> where the Electors of the <hi>Empire</hi> were met upon the Election of the King of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and they did so blazon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad the great Revolution, which from day to day would be declared, that they kept the aforesaid Electors in suspence, as likewise the other Ministers, who were there employed about that impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant affair; neither did this news (which the enemies had spread abroad) give a small disturbance to the King of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> the <hi>Arch-Duke,</hi> and the Count <hi>de Pennaranda;</hi> till such time as their minds were quieted by the arrival of a Post, sent away by <hi>Don John,</hi> with the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I made him, who parted from <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xell</hi>'s the next day after this happened; for I stay'd but that night, leaving <hi>Ostend</hi> at the very instant, that we had convoy'd the Mareshall to the Governour's house, which was about three in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon. And those that are at <hi>Frankfort</hi> write from thence, that this News has so confounded the arrogance of the <hi>French</hi> there, that they appear not in the streets.</p>
            <pb n="128" facs="tcp:41743:70"/>
            <p>But to return to our Enemies: being disembarked, they began to form a Squadron of 1500. men upon the <hi>Cay,</hi> which was nearest to the Town; the Governour thought it fit to disperse and scatter them; and so with his own hands he pull'd down the white Flag, which had been set up as a Signal upon the great Bulwark, and commanded a Vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of Musket-shot to be given them, which was the first warning they had to disabuse themselves; upon which each man began to shift for himself.</p>
            <p>The Artillery playing too soon upon the Ships which entred, was the only error that was committed in this Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it hindering five Vessells from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring; and especially, a great Frigate, in which were all the Chief Officers of the <hi>English</hi> Fleet, who were invited by the Mareshall to Dinner,; and these be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing within ten or twelve paces of the Shelff, tack't about, with others that did not come in, in which, they said, there were the 200000 <hi>Florins,</hi> sent by Capitulation for the Garrison; but for
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:41743:70"/> my part, I do not believe there was one farthing, because 'tis seldome that Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors are so punctually dealt withall.</p>
            <p>Marshall <hi>De Aumont,</hi> with two Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of the King's Guard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and some other particular persons, fled over the drowned Lands, thinking to save them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves by crossing the Haven, and so ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king towards the Downs, over against the Town; there went about 150. of them w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th their Arms: that way was well found out by them, had it not been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by an Ambush of 300. Horse, with good Officers, who received them with many complements.</p>
            <p>By this time I was sallied forth with an Adjutant of <hi>Don Antonio Furtado</hi>'s <hi>Tercia,</hi> and a dozen <hi>Spanish</hi> Musketteers, running to and fro along the Bank, and the over-flowed-land, in pursuit of the <hi>Mareshall,</hi> and Monsieur <hi>Talou,</hi> who escaped me, in regard I knew him not; the latter of the two having whispered a pleasant note, and gratefull to the ears of a Captain of <hi>Spanish</hi> Foot, to the Tune of 300. Pistolls, although
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:41743:71"/> his ransome was worth 20000. he hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a far greater imployment than his Military, and not having Quarter, but at discretion. Whether the Captain, in this particular, abused the King, or no, I shall not take upon me to judge; I know it was pass'd by, by which it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, not to be capital.</p>
            <p>Above 300. men flung down their Armes altogether, upon a Sign I gave them, telling them, they were betray'd, as they might perceive by the dead, and the wounded, wich amounted not to 200. the rest being all taken Prisoners of War, and being stript, were sent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to several Towns. The <hi>Mareshall,</hi> and some Noble Persons with him, were treated with all civility and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect, his <hi>Highness</hi> recommending them to the Castle at <hi>Antwerp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Mareshall</hi> was very desirous to have entred the Town in the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour's Coach, pretending himself to be hurt in the Heel, of which he halted, because he would not passe shamefully through the Crowd; but 'twas not
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:41743:71"/> thought fit; but rather, that the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and the Burgers, who were hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somely drawn up in the streets, and in all the chief places of the Town, should have the joy, and satisfaction to see those taken, who had so long watch'd to have taken them; by which means this day was a day of Jubily for <hi>Ostend,</hi> and all those who were concerned in it.</p>
            <p>Here, Sir, you have a Relation at large, of all that passed, with the happy conclusion of the success, which we owe to his <hi>Highness,</hi> who by his wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome knew how to begin it, carry it on, and end it, according to our hearts desire.</p>
            <p>An ingenious person might here find field-room enough to enlarge himself, and to adorn and illustrate this Story, both with Moral and Political observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, upon the variety of changes, and the miraculous secresie; But I who have other Irons in the Fire, shall leave it to such who profess writing, and have the faculty of applying the thoughts of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men to their own. And shall end
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:41743:72"/> with telling you, Colonel <hi>Spintelet</hi> was rewarded with a Regiment of <hi>Walloon</hi> Foot; and Advocate <hi>de Bocq,</hi> who was so indefatigable in the pains he took, was made Councellour of <hi>Flanders,</hi> and Attorney General of the Province. These rewards were deservedly bestow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and may be good motives for every one, to make use of that Talent God hath given him: They have left me (who likewise bore my share in the Brunt) puff'd up with the pride and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of having acted my part well in this Farce; with which I am as fully sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, as they with their rewards; and should be more if this rough draught be acceptable to you, whom God preserve: Which is the vote of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Yours.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:41743:72"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>